Um hello everyone. Um am I audible?
Okay, cool. Yeah. Uh sorry for being a
bit late. Sorry. Uh okay, I'm not
audible. Uh Shubra says I'm not audible.
I'm audible to others in the class. I'm
audible. Okay. So, let me ask Shubra to
rejoin.
Cool. Okay. Uh so let me share my screen
and then we get started.
Cool. Uh, let me share my screen. Just
give me a minute.
Okay. So, I think I'll have to restart
my iPad. It's not showing up. But yeah,
anyhow, in the meanwhile, uh I'm not
sure how many of you know me uh or have
uh seen me here or there. So, my name is
Sarn Maluta. I am a software engineer at
Google and roughly a year and a half
ago, I used to lead the learning
learning vertical at Scaler Academy. Uh
since then, I've moved from my full-time
role at Scala and I keep on taking uh
classes uh for the HLD module and DSL DS
algo module etc. Uh I can I will share
my LinkedIn profile with you guys. I can
do it right now or I can share it at the
end of the lecture. But yeah, since my
iPad needs a restart, I can do it right
away. And yeah, it has uh so why am I
taking your lecture today? Given that
Pug is taking this batch, I am taking
other batch um simultaneously. But yeah,
uh I am taking your class today because
Pug is unavailable. But uh don't worry
uh I I promise that you are going to
have a great time and we are going to
understand the concepts that we have for
today quite well and I am uh I have been
teaching HLD at Scala for several years
now. So uh you don't have to I of course
it it's very uh it's very obvious that
when you are uh taking a bunch of
classes from somebody and you have a
instructor change a day you essentially
uh get worried and feel that hey am I
going to understand the things the way I
used to so you don't have to worry uh we
are going to understand today's concepts
very well cool uh so I have reset my
iPad and let me try and uh g share it
that's right sat I yeah
uh let me let me restart uh let me re
try and reach reshare my iPad. Yeah,
it's visible now and you should be able
to see or see my iPad screen in just a
minute.
Yeah, I'm a software engineer at Google.
Uh cool.
Okay. So now uh what all have you guys
studied till now in the high level
design module. Uh you have studied
things uh you have studied the very
basics of high level design. You have
understood that hey how does a system
scale from a single machine and go on to
spread across multiple machines. If you
have uh if if you have a bunch of if you
have a system which has a good scale how
do you spread across multiple machines
and get your job done? You would have
discussed about consistent hashing. You
would have also discussed about how to
make a system a lot more faster, how to
make it having a lot less latency and
for that you would have discussed
caching. There are different kinds of
caching that you can throw in. You can
have a client side cache where you can
cache a bunch of things on browser.
There can be a you can have a thing like
content delivery network or CDN so that
you have some data some media files
nearer to the user so that the user can
access them quickly. That's the idea of
CDNs. Then you might have app server
cache where the compute boxes that you
have might have something cached so that
they can compute the things quicker and
you also can have a global cache where
you have a separate layer where you
cache something and all your app server
boxes can interact with that global
cache and get your job done. Is
everybody with me till this Monday
night? You would have understood all of
this over several classes uh that you
have had with Paka. Uh now one more
thing uh that somebody asks that hey I
have not attended the caching lecture
can I still attend today's lecture and
understand the content of today you can
Sachin it's not directly correlated to
caching but one general advice that I
have for everybody for the HL module
specifically that you should try and
attend all the classes in the sequence
that in the sequence that they occur and
be prepared with the content of the
previous classes before you join the
next class that's the usual advice that
I would have but for today's lecture
even if you have not attending C
attended caching you will still be able
to understand most of it cool so let's
get started
let's draw a diagram that I'm sure that
you have seen multiple times that hey
this is how the interaction between the
client and the system looks like you
have a client
the client reaches out to the DNS
because the client just has usually the
domain name but to reach any resource on
the internet you need the IP address. So
you go to the DNS give the domain name
fetch the IP address from there. So you
get the IP address back. Using this IP
address you can you can reach out to the
system. The first box that interacts
with the outside world is usually called
the gateway box right it's called the
gateway box. So Pratia might have called
it the load balancer. I will maybe
discuss uh or we can discuss it right
now. By gateway I mean the first box
that acts as a gateway for any outside
request to the inside system. You people
also call it the load balancer box
because this box usually doubles up as a
load balancer. So what is the meaning of
a load balancer? Load balancer basically
means that a box that is going to
distribute the load amongst multiple uh
multiple other resources. Right? This
gateway acts as a load balancer. But if
you look at from it look at it from the
outside the first box that box that
interacts is essentially called a
gateway box right so we will discuss
about proxy and reverse proxy but you
are right Munali that's what it is uh
yeah so the gateway box is where uh you
do a bunch of things right other than
load balancing you do a bunch of other
things also and that's why I am calling
it a gateway box because you not only do
load balancing here but you also do
things like some uh for example there is
a HTTPS request coming from the outside
world you might want that request to be
decifered here itself and you can
interact with the internal world using a
internal ecosystem using a totally
different protocol so but all of that we
will cover maybe sometime later it's not
the right class to discuss all of that
but just understand that gateway has a
lot of other responsibilities other than
just being a load balancer does that
make sense to everybody you can call it
a load balancer but that's one aspect of
it. There are a bunch of other aspects
of it. You can call it a gateway which
is a much more generic name because it
acts as the first point of contact for
the outside world. Now after the gateway
you're going to have a bunch of app
server boxes.
Now this is your compute layer right
this is the place where your computation
happen where all the magic happens where
all the computation whatever is the
business logic actually runs here right.
So this is the gateway box. Uh yeah
Koshik that's right. So most of the
companies usually end the uh the SSL
terminates at the gateway box and then
internally you follow a different
protocol. Uh these apps ser are
microservices. No s we are going to
discuss what microservices are in later
part of the curriculum. For now, just
understand this is a box that will
interact with the outside world and will
forward the request to a bunch of
different resources because a single
compute box, a single app server box may
not be able to handle all the load and
hence you have a bunch of apps server
boxes that will together handle the load
for you. Is that making sense to
everybody in the class? That's the
reason why you would want to have
multiple app servers. If your traffic to
the to the service increases, you might
want to spawn a bunch of new app server
boxes. If the traffic goes low, you
might want to remove a bunch of app
server boxes. How many of you have uh
seen autoscaling in cloud services like
AWS, right? So, you autoscale. If you
have a lot of higher traffic, you
increase these app server boxes. If you
have lesser amount of traffic, you
reduce these app server boxes. Now,
there are some people who did not uh
follow autoscaling. It's not part of
today's class, but I will just give you
an example, right? Uh how many of you
appreciate that the traffic let's say
Amazon.com has on a Black Friday sale or
Flipkart has on a big billion day sale
is going to be very different from a
normal day at Flipkart or a normal day
at Amazon. How many of you understand
that there's going to be a lot of
difference between the traffic? Right?
Not only that, let's consider some more
examples. uh let's assume that hey there
is a there is a day uh
let's say it's a it's a Diwali week
right the traffic on Diwali week it's
going to be a lot higher than traffic on
a normal week Munali has given an
example of hot star that traffic on hot
star on an India Pakistan match is going
to be much higher than a traffic than
the traffic on hot star when there is no
live cricket match happening right uh so
the the the the scale or the traffic at
which needs to be suburbed by the system
does not follow a very static
trajectory. The traffic keeps on going
up and down with respect to seasons,
with respect to times of the day, with
respect to events. That is why you
should have the flexibility or the
correct system design word is the
elasticity in order to scale up your
compute and scale down your compute
accordingly. Am I making sense? On the
days or at the times when the traffic is
high, you might want to have a lot more
compute resources. On the day or the
time when the traffic is low, you would
not want to have a lot of compute
resources, right? So that's the reason
that's elasticity and that's that's what
your multiple app servers also support.
I hope I have made myself clear. Cool.
Beyond this, we have discussed the
storage layer where the data actually
gets stored, right? This is where the
data gets persisted forever. this is
your ultimate source of truth. Uh so
would have discussed this kind of a
architecture with you. He might have
also told that okay for a global cache
you might have a parallel layer where
you store something globally as a cache
and you can access that from your app
servers rather quickly as compared to
the database boxes. Great. All of this
makes sense. Uh this is all hunky dory.
We all appreciate it. We are all happy
about it. In today's class, what is
serverless? Uh Rahul. So Rahul we will
discuss about uh this maybe later not in
today's class because I have a bunch of
things to cover and this is not the
right time to cover serverless but
serless architecture is a an
architecture which which I will maybe
talk about slightly later okay so we are
going to maybe build towards
a place where understanding serless
becomes becomes easier but discussing
serless right now is not the right time
because we need a lot of other blocks to
fall into place. Cool. So now I'm going
to discuss in today's class the idea of
cap theorem. Uh and we'll also discuss
another extension of that theorem called
base LC and then I will talk about
master slave architecture. I will talk
about replication as in general I will
talk about uh all of these concepts in
as much detail as possible. Whatever
questions you have would love to answer
all of them for you. Okay cool. So I
want everybody's attention. We are going
to discuss gap theorem.
to begin with.
Uh okay, sharding is also discussed. So
let's actually let's actually do what
Vas
Prasad is trying us to take into. They
say that okay sharding is also
discussed. So let's start with sharding
and build towards partitioning and then
come to cap theorem. Okay. So what is
sharding? First of all, can anybody in
the class appreciate for me help me
appreciate what sharding is? Okay,
sharding was not discussed in detail.
So, Ashit, your complaint about sharding
not being discussed in detail will be
discussed today. Okay. Uh let's uh let's
resolve that complaint. Cool. So, what
is sharding? Sharding essentially is the
idea that there might be a lot of data
that you have to store which cannot sit
on a single machine. How many of you
appreciate it that let's assume uh you
have to store uh you have to store user
DBs for Facebook. Okay. So let's discuss
that. Let's say you want to store the
user database
of Facebook.
I'm sure Prague would have discussed uh
Facebook news feed. Do you remember what
was the ballpark number that he that he
gave you for the number of users
Facebook has? What was the ballpark
number? Or even if you don't remember
it, just just help me understand. What's
the ballpark number that you think uh 8
billion?
How many people are there in this world?
7 billion if I'm not wrong. Right. So uh
somebody just mentioned that there are 8
billion Facebook users, which means that
Facebook has users beyond the world.
That's that's a that's a new thing to
understand. Okay. Fake accounts. Okay.
Makes sense. Makes sense. So, Facebook,
in my opinion, would have a few billion
users. Overall users might have a few
billion overall users. Okay. Let's
assume maybe 3 billion users, right?
Your daily active users, monthly active
users is maybe 1 billion. Uh from the
data that I remember, monthly active
users at Facebook is roughly 1 billion
and daily active users if I'm not wrong
is roughly around.5 billion. Uh so this
is the usual number of uh users that
Facebook has. Now if you want to store
the user database for 3 billion users do
you think one box one storage machine is
able will will be able to maybe store
three billion entries three billion data
points maybe not right because let's try
to understand what all Facebook have
right so Facebook might have a users
table what all will the users table
contain my dear friends it will contain
things like user ID
It will then maybe contain the name of
the user. Might also contain the gender
of the user. Might also contain the
relationship status of the user. Might
also contain a bunch of other
information about the user and might
also contain last updated created etc.
Am I making sense to everybody? There
would be a bunch of metadata about every
user. Right? This is one table that we
can imagine in the user DB of Facebook.
Let's understand some more. Uh, of
course, there will be uh maybe a link to
the display picture, maybe a link to the
cover picture, etc. What else does
Facebook will Facebook have about users?
If I am not wrong, uh, all of you will
be able to appreciate that Facebook
should also store the information about
the user friends, right? Because friends
are the connections form the bedrock of
Facebook. So you would want to also have
a table where you have user friends
table right. Uh now user friends table
will have something like this that you
will have a user ID and then you will
have a friend ID right. So for example
if there is a user 107 whose name is
Raju. So let's assume you have user ID
107 with the name Raju. Raju happens to
be a male. their relationship status is
that they are uh let's say they are
married
and we have some last last updated
information we have the date of birth we
have a bunch of other metadata about
them similarly Raju has a bunch of other
friends as well so let's say Raju with
the user ID 107 has a friend with the
user ID 998 so of course there would be
an entry for 998 also in this in this
table so 998 happens to be another user
who Raj Raju is friends with similarly
Raju might also be friends with let's
say Kiriti and Kiri might have another
user ID let's say 1070 let's say yeah
Raju might also be friends with another
person whose uh friend whose user ID
might be 66 guys am I making sense so
you will want to have information about
the user and their meta information and
you would also want to have information
about user and their friends now let's
assume that these two are the primary
tables that right now we want to
consider while thinking about a user DB
a user database. Now my dear friends
with three billion entries in the users
table and many many more billion entries
in the user friends table. Do you
understand that a single machine will
not be able to support all of that? You
cannot potentially store all of that in
a single machine. Why? Because the
machine needs to be a super machine
which needs to handle maybe 100 TB of
data. uh just assuming this sums up to
100 TB or or you or you al also might
have a scenario where a single machine
might not be able to handle all that
load, right? Storing data about every
single person on Facebook and then
responding to requests that come with
respect to that uh data is not going to
be simple. How many of you are convinced
that storing all of this in a single
machine is not possible?
uh I want more people to uh tarun of
course we can calculate the rough amount
of data storage required for all of this
I'm not doing that right now because I
want to save on time we will be doing
this in a lot of other use cases that we
will do where the class is entirely
going to be about a use case we will do
all the calculation together do all the
back of the envelope calculations but
right now I am just trying to save some
time and not do it okay but it's uh you
are going to learn how to do it in the
further classes is we are going to in
all the case studies that we discussed
we are going to spend the first 15 20
minutes doing estimation of scale and
there all these calculations will come.
Okay cool. So now we have understood
that a single machine will not be not be
enough
to overcome this problem. Two concepts
the concept of sharding and the concept
of partitioning or replication.
Let's say sharding and replication.
These two concepts become very very
important and we are going to discuss
them. uh sharding should already have
been discussed but we are going to
discuss sharding and replication and
give you some sense of that today and
then we will discuss cap theorem pile
etherum etc right so understand what is
sharding sharding is the idea of
distributing or dividing this data into
multiple machines because a single
machine cannot store all that data okay
so what is sharding
Sharding is
distributing data
across
multiple
machines. Uh let me draw a diagram so
that this becomes important. This
becomes this becomes more clear. Let's
assume this is the universe of all the
radar that you want to have. Okay. So
you will have data about the user 107.
You will have data about the user 998.
You will have data about the user 107
1070 etc. Sharding basically means that
you cannot store all this universe of
data in a single machine. You use a
bunch of machines to get this done. So
all the data points in this segment of
the universe I will put in shard A or
the first shard. All the data on this
segment of the universe I will let's say
put on shard B. All the data on this
segment of the universe I will put in
shard C. All the data in this part of
the universe I will put in shard D. All
the data in this part of the universe I
will put in shard Eyee. How many of you
understand this? that in a way I will
distribute my data universe into
mutually exclusive and together
exhaustive way so that all the shards
together have all the data together and
no two shards have the same data guys am
I making some sense sharding basically
means partitioning the data guys am I
making sense
right you can distribute uh you can
distribute equally you can distribute
based on geography etc etc
All of that is going to be decided based
on the use case that you have. Guys, am
I making sense? This can be a random
allocation. This can be a geographical
allocation. This can be a time based
allocation etc etc. There can be
different ways in which you would want
to do this allocation. But that's a you
that's a use case specific thing. But
all of you appreciate what sharding is,
right? Sharding is distribute your data
across multiple machines because a
single machine cannot potentially store
it. Now if you remember Pra would have
discussed consistent hashing with you.
You remember that inconsistent hashing
pra would have drawn a logical circle
and he would have shared that okay this
is shard A this is shard B this is shard
C this is shard D.
All the different A B C D or 1 2 3 4
servers that you would have written here
all of them are distinct shards. Am I
making sense?
Am I making sense? So all of these were
shards. Okay, this is sh these are
shards.
Cool. So sharding is a concept clear to
everybody that if you cannot store all
the data in a single machine, you shard.
Okay, Rohit, it's not clear to Rohit.
Rohit, would you want to be unmuted? I
can unmute you and I can answer your
question. Rohit, do you want me to
unmute it? Okay, let me unmute Rohit.
Hey Rohit.
Hi Ajit I will answer this question for
you in a just short h. Yeah. So my
question is whatever the sharing we are
making for the all the database in
multiple machine. So we are following
any specific pattern or equal data we
are uh pushing into another machine or
how it uh works. So like replica kind of
data
>> okay replication is totally different. I
will come to replication in a while.
Sharding is you distributing the radar
across multiple machines. So uh let's
let's go back to the Facebook example,
right? And uh Ajit's question will also
get answered with this explanation.
Okay. So I want everybody's complete
attention here. Uh I have told you that
there are going to be uh let's say three
billion users of Facebook. So how many
entries are there going to be in this
user table, right? My dear friends, if
for every user I have one entry and
there are three billion users, how many
entries will I have? Three billion.
>> Three billion.
Now what I want to uh tell you and Ajit
I want your attention as well is that
rather than storing all three billion
entries in the same machine I can do
sharding. What does that mean? That
means that okay a bunch of these entries
or a bunch of I I am taking an example
where I'm going to do sharding based on
user ID. So I will be taking a bunch of
user ids and say that these user ids
belong to shard A.
I will take a bunch of other user ids
and say these user ids belong in shard B
because a single machine cannot save it.
I am distributing them in different
shards. I will take a bunch of other uh
user ids and say these should be present
in shard C and so on and so forth. This
is one thing. The second thing is that
for the user ids that I selected in
shard A,
all the entries in the user friends
table with that user ID, I will also be
picking all those entries and ensuring
they also go in shard A. In a way, in a
way I have used the user ID as a key to
determine which shard do they belong
into. Imagine this to be a collection of
databases where a subsegment of users
sit in database A. A subsegment of users
sit in database B. A subsegment of users
sit in database C. But calling it a
individual database might not be the
right way to call it because it's
basically one database but given one
machine could not potentially store all
the data. I have distributed that data
across multiple machines. I'm calling
every machine, every database instance a
shard. Does it make sense to everybody?
Roit. Does it make sense to you? Yeah.
So only the thing like so whatever the
data you are sharding that you're
sharding the size of data will be the
random correct
that that's totally dependent on a use
case right now I am saying I'm going to
sh based on a user ID if you remember if
you remember consistent hashing how did
that happen you had a h for server or
you had multiple hash functions for
servers because you don't want cascading
failure but forget cascading failure for
a while and just understand that there
was a hash server which sort of helped
you mark different servers on different
parts of the circle. Then there was a
edge request or they would have called
it edge user or something else where you
pass the user ID to determine where does
this user sit into or you pass the
request ID to figure out where does this
request go to. So you mark that request
and then you move in the in the
clockwise direction to find which server
does it belong to. So there can be
multiple ways in which you can shard.
One of the ways can be that you use user
ID as the starting key to determine this
user ID will go in this box. You can use
the request ID as a sharding key. You
can use something else as a sharding
key. But for now just imagine user ID as
the sharding key which will help you
determine which box this user is going
to be in. Am I making sense?
>> Yeah, that's correct. So only one thing
is pending. So whatever like in Facebook
example we are taking. So whatever the
user id we are storing into the uh
specific shard we are storing the uh
correspondence friend also. So that
means
>> right we are storing the corresponding
friends also and there is a reason for
that. uh you might not be able to
appreciate the reason right now but in
the storage classes I will be able to
make that make you appreciate the reason
but I will just give you a small piece
of information so that you are intrigued
and you are interested to know more but
I will not fulfill your interest and
answer all of that today because I have
a topic to complete but just to tickle
your interest try to understand it's a
very common query for people to know who
all my friends are Rohit is that correct
>> correct
>> it's very common for people to know who
all my friends are or I am an avid
Facebook user. I might want to go to
your profile. I'm not that kind of a
person but just assume that I might want
to go to your profile and know who all
your friends are. Right?
>> So this is a very common query.
>> Now understand if I don't put all the
rows where I can know 107's friend in
the same database as 107 exists then
knowing which all friends I have will
require me to go to different shards and
collect the data.
>> Okay. Which all friends are mine which
are in this shard? Which all friends are
mine in this shard? Which all friends
are mine in this shard? The join will
become very different difficult. On the
other hand, if I ensure that all the
entries related to 107 sit in the same
shard, the join becomes in easy because
you are in the same box and you just
have to run a simple query in the same
box and get the answer. So that is the
reason why you would want to put the
friend entries also in the same chart.
But this is just a small piece of notion
that I gave to tickle your interest.
We'll discuss this in more details in
the storage classes. Yeah.
>> Does that make sense to you Rohit?
>> Yeah. Yeah, that got it. Thanks.
>> Okay. Thanks a lot, man. Thanks a lot.
Uh Adit Ajit also asked similar
questions. Ajit, is that clear to you as
well, my dear friend? Ajit, is it clear
to you as well? Uh I am not sure if Ajit
is there in the class or not, but he has
a simple similar question and I hope
it's clear to him as well. It is that's
great. Cool. So I am seeing a bunch of
other questions that I will pick a bit
later but just to get a brief sense how
many people of how many people in the
class are with me. How many of you
understand what sharding is? How many
feel interested that hey this is a great
concept sharding we now understand it
when data is very big. How do you
distribute it in multiple machines uh in
a mutually exclusive and collectively
exhaustive way? This is what is called
as sharding. So I will write this
beautiful phrase also. You would have
heard this in your DS algo classes most
likely. It's called uh mutually
exhaustive.
So sorry mutually exclusive collectively
exhaustive. Mutually exclusive
collectively exhausted.
So everybody here understands
uh what is sharding. Okay. Now I want
everybody to focus on the different
concept. I have taught maybe thousands
of people and I've interacted with maybe
a lot more people about about HLD or
designing systems at scale. One thing
that I see again and again is people
confusing between sharding and
replication.
I want to ensure that after today's
class, none of you are ever going to be
confused between sharding and
replication. Okay, these are two
different concepts. They mean different
things and we have to ensure that we
understand what difference they are, how
different they are. Okay, so sharding is
clear to everyone. You have a lot of
data you distributed in multiple
machines, right? Uh yeah. Yeah, Basia,
you are right. So I will take the
questions later and now I will continue
with what I have to teach. Right. Uh
okay lalit I understand that uh I
understand that uh now what is the idea
of replication
I want everybody's attention complete
attention here let's say let's say there
is a single machine
okay and a lot of people want to read
data from this machine so let's say this
machine stores all the post that that
Justin Bieber has made. Now,
unfortunately or fortunately, we live in
a world where people are going to be
super interested in knowing what Justin
Bieber has posted. So, everybody is
rushing to know uh see a copy of Justin
Bieber's post and everybody wants to see
it. So, this machine given it maintains
the copies or it maintains the post of
Justin Bieber, this machine is going to
have a lot of read requests. Am I making
sense to everybody that the read
requests here are going to be a lot
higher?
Now try to understand every single
machine has its own limitations. You
cannot handle beyond a threshold read
request parallelly. You cannot handle
beyond a threshold write requests
parallelly. There's a limit to how many
requests you can handle every minute. So
this is where the idea of replication
comes in.
Now what is replication? Replication
basically means that a single copy of
the data is getting overwhelmed because
of the high number of requests. Hence
you create multiple copies of the same
data so that people can read from
different copies of the same data. So
you have one let's say rather than
having just one copy of the same data
you have a bunch of replicas right we
are going to discuss this in a lot more
detail at the end of the lecture but you
have a bunch of replicas where you
replicate the entries
and now some people can go and read from
this box some people can go and read
from this box some people can go and
read from this box and so on and so
forth. So do you understand that you
might want to have copies of the same
data? This is called as replication. Is
everybody in the class with me? What is
replication? You maintaining copies of
the same data. Right? Now of course
there are going to be lot of questions
that hey what kind of a copies are
these? Do we call this master slave? Uh
how does read happen? How do right
happen? E etc etc. I'm going to I'm
going to cover all these questions at
the end of the lecture. But guys, do you
appreciate what replication is?
Replication is you creating copies of
the same data so that more people can
interact with the copies together.
How many of you appreciate that this is
completely different from sharding? How
many of you appreciate this is
completely different from sharding?
Sharding was you distributing the data
in different machines. Replication is
you copying the same data in different
machines. So replication is not mutually
exclusive, right? Replication is you
copying the same data. Sharding is you
distributing the data. So if somebody
calls partitioning, partitioning is what
you can call as uh a kind of sharding.
Guys, am I making sense? Partitioning
creating partitions creating. Okay. So
Nikl says no. So I understand why do you
say no to calling partitioning
equivalent to sharding? I will come back
to it later. Partitioning is different.
But partitioning uh maybe you are
confusing Nikl this with with network
partitioning you're confusing this with
partition tolerance right so that's also
what I'm going to discuss today but for
now given that we are going to discuss
another topic with the similar name
right I would want to maybe remove this
partitioning for now but later once I
cover network partitioning I will maybe
come back and discuss what is data
partitioning okay guys so I will come
back and discuss what is data
partitioning but For now, I want
everybody's agreement that what is
sharding and what is replication? These
are two different things. Is everybody
in the class with me? Is everybody in
the class with me? I want everybody in
the class to answer. Uh nobody should be
so lazy that they can't use their mouse
and let me know that hey, they are with
me. Everybody should be able to tell me
that they are with me. Right? Good. So,
we understand what is sharding, what is
replication. Uh Anurag, I will come to
that. Replication is you copying the
same data
on different machines. Sharding is you
distributing the data dividing it into
multiple machines. Am I making sense to
everybody in the class?
Right now
sharding and replication can exist
together
and I will help you understand that as
well. Okay. So let's say there are 3
billion users of Facebook. There are 3
billion users at Facebook.
I cannot store them in the same machine.
So what do I do? I shard.
So I create shards, right? There are
going to be maybe a few hundred or a few
thousand shards or maybe a few hundred
shards. So I create shards. Maybe data
for 107 is present here. 9070 is present
here. 1070 is here, 66 is here, 442 is
here, and so on and so forth. So you
have different user ids in different
charts. Does everybody understand this?
Does everybody understand this that you
have a bunch of shards? Now let's assume
even for the you even for the people who
are in the same shard, the number of
requests are so high that a single
machine cannot handle them. a single
machine. So try to understand sharding
was based on the storage requirements.
How many of you understand that that
there are tbs and tbs of data you can't
put it in the same machine?
Your replication is primarily driven by
the number of requests that are coming.
So the number of requests that you are
seeing are so huge that a single machine
cannot handle them. So what do you do?
You now treat every shard
and create replicas of that shard. Okay.
Yeah, Raju, I'm trying to write as much
as I can. So, you can have
replica. So, let me call this as shard
one, shard two, shard three.
And now I will have a replica of this
shard one. I will have another replica
of this shard one. Similarly, I will
have a rep I will have replicas for
shard two.
Similarly, I will have replicas for
shard 3.
So you can say that okay
this is replica one for shard one. This
is replica two for shard two. This is
replica one for shard two. Sorry this is
replica. Okay. So this was replica one
for shard one. This was replica one for
shard replica two for shard one guys. I
hope I'm making sense. I hope I'm making
sense. This is replica one of shard two.
This is replica two of shard two. This
is replica one of shard three. This is
replica two of shard three. Am I making
sense to everybody in the class? Replica
is where the same piece of information
is stored as a replica. Sharding is you
dividing data amongst different
machines. So sharding and replication
can exist simultaneously
which I have taken an example to explain
to all of you. Replication is basically
clones you maintaining clones. Is
everybody in the class with me? Is this
clear? Sharding replication. All clear.
All clear. There is one down vote. I can
maybe Anybody wants to be unmuted?
Anybody wants to be unmuted?
Anybody wants to be unmuted? Okay. Arun
doesn't want to be unmuted. Uh okay,
cool. Nobody wants to be unmuted. Maybe
everybody is scared that if I get
unmuted and I eat up class's time, then
everybody is going to come after me.
Maybe this is the worry that people
have. Uh but yeah, don't be worried. If
you have something to ask, you can of
course ask. Uh or you can of course ask
at the end of the lecture as well. I
hope everybody's with me till this point
in time. Uh
yeah, I can unmute you my dear friend.
Hey Akil, please go on. Karuma Karumi
asks, "What if we don't want all the
records in the shark to have a replica?"
Uh Karumi, why would you not want to
have that? Why would you not want to
replicate the entire shard but only
replicate a part of the shard? Uh I
don't see a reason why you would want to
do that. Hey, please tell me.
>> Yeah. Uh yeah, Taran. So the shards are
nothing but a DB, right? Uh or is it a
server?
>> So shame
database mean
>> uh sorry I missed. So these are database
boxes. These are database instances. By
shards I mean that they are so every
shard is a database instance storing
some data. Another shard is database
instance storing some other data. So all
of them for example if you are using uh
my SQL all of them are going to be MySQL
boxes. If you're using uh Cassandra all
of them are going to be Cassandra nodes.
If you're using uh HBS all of them are
going to be HBS nodes. Am I making
sense?
>> Yeah. And the replica replica also will
be the same. they will also be the same.
So uh if if uh all of them are SQL
boxes, the replicas also are going to be
SQL boxes as a picture.
>> Okay. Yeah. And do we do this
dynamically or do we have them fixed
before itself based on the request? Do
we do dynamically or like
>> No, no, no. So, so you would never want
to move your data dynamically. Request
the compute layer is a lot more dynamic
in nature, but the storage layer is a
lot more static. Right? So let me ask
you a question. I'm not sure if you have
seen that in your present organization
or not but uh you and I want I I'm
asking this question to everybody in the
class. I want everybody to comment on
what I'm saying right now. You have seen
that your EC2 instances if you use AWS
or your compute resources they kept keep
getting scaled up and scaled down that
you have 20 EC2 instances right now in
the next hour you have 30 EC2 instance
running. you scale up or scale down your
compute layer very easily because they
are just computing some data but you
don't do that okay I have I have 10
database boxes running just in the next
1 hour I will have 20 database boxes
running or I will just let an intern to
cut my 10 database boxes to five
database boxes right because your
storage is a lot more static and
predictable but your compute is a lot
more erratic requires a lot more
elasticity Am I making sense again? So
you don't uh radically just keep on
changing your databases. They are
planned well ahead of time. Your compute
can radically change.
>> No, I mean the replicas uh which we are
using. So those will be dynamic or like
we'll be uh in
>> right. So dynamic is a very dynamic is a
very open-ended term, right? You can
mean dynamic in a lot of different ways.
Uh but but the point of the matter is
that you won't have a scenario where
your where your data keeps on moving
between different boxes all the time.
You will have a specific shard to take
care of a bunch of data points. The rep
if if by stat if by uh if by dynamic you
mean are these slave replicas on the
same box? Can they move between boxes
etc. That's something that we will study
in greater detail in the kind of
database that we study. So this is not
the right time for me to answer that
question. Okay.
>> Yeah. Okay. Sure. Thank you so much.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Now, there is a
question in the chat which says that
what if I need more database. When you
need more database, when you need more
storage, then that's something which you
pre-plan. It's not as if the case you
immediately understand that you require
more data. You you for example you have
a 500 GB box. You see the data storage
increasing. The moment it reaches let's
say 350GB, 70% of your data storage is
utilized. You already pre pre-plan and
try to accommodate more data by adding
another shard. Hassan, am I making
sense? You don't quickly radically take
database decisions. You pre-plan, you
then make these sharding decisions, etc.
Okay, I will unmute a few more people. I
see Rajie's hand raised. So, Rajiv,
please go on.
>> Hi, Ton. Yeah, my question was as you
see as you said like uh we will have a
data segregation based on some user ID
or maybe some of the parameter right
which basically we will see like what is
the most common pattern based on that we
going to segregate the data
>> right so for different use cases you
will have different sharding keys right
>> correct but uh uh what I'm seeing the
problem like how if if suppose this
taking this as a example we have
multiple users in S1 S2 S3 so if I have
a page where I have to show all the
users then how the query will basically
work and how we going to optimize that
thing over here because I'm seeing this
as a doing the sharding on multiple
multiple
>> so basically what you are what you're
pointing at Rajie is called as a concept
of intrashard request and intershard
requests. There are going to be some
requests that can be handled within a
shard and there are going to be some
requests that require you to go to
multiple shards and then compute the
answer.
>> Correct.
>> Intrashard requests are a lot more
optimal. Intershard requests are a lot
less optimal. We will discuss multiple
systems and we will see how to make most
of our requests intrashard and how can
we avoid intershard as much as possible
because intershard requests are going to
be very very dreadful. So if you
remember that uh uh truck would have
discussed the Facebook uh news feed
example right?
>> Yes.
>> He would have told you that I would
rather cash the recent posts.
>> Yeah. uh and I will rather put pull them
from the same database. The reason was
that Prager did not want you to design a
system where you will go to different
machines and query this machine please
tell me the latest post. This machine
please tell me the latest post. This
machine please tell me the latest post
because if you do that then you are
overwhelming the entire network. Your
requests are reaching every shard which
is a very very dreadful thing to do. So
we we figure out ways to avoid
intershard requests and the way that
prairie would have taught you in the
last class would have been that I am
going to use a recent DB a recent post
DB from where I'm going to fetch it. So
I'm going to convert my intershard
request into a single machine request
and which is going to be optimal. But
this is something that we'll discuss
again and again in the following storage
classes. Uh but I have given you a short
answer, right?
>> Yeah. Yes. Thank you very much.
Thanks a lot Rajie. Karun Karum Karun
Maji your time. Your turn. Yeah. Hi K.
So my question is like suppose a shard
has like around thousand users like user
data. So out of thousand user data like
100 people are like most influential or
like having more more number of follows
and getting more number of read
requests. So we don't need to replicate
all the 900 users in the same DB. We
just wanted to replicate only the 100.
Got it. In that case, you would rather
than Okay, so there are two ways to
First of all, this is a this is a hot
shard problem, right? This is a problem
which is called as in the in the in the
high level design lingo called as hot
shard. You have a shard which has a lot
of requests coming. That's that's a
that's something that we might discuss
later. This is not the right time to
discuss it. But
>> to answer your specific question, there
are two different kinds of uh there are
two different kinds of ways that you can
look at this problem. One is that you
can say that okay I would want to only
replicate a few data points of the
chart. That's very difficult to manage,
very difficult to implement, very
difficult to imagine, very difficult to
keep a track of. You would not want to
go that route. The other way to do that
would be that you might want to have a
hot shard. You might want to have a
shard which has a few popular users in
them. You might want to have other
shards which are cold shards which are
people like you and me. Nobody comes to
our profiles. Nobody's interested in
knowing what's happening in our lives.
So we have very few requests. Right? So
there might be few shards which are cold
shards. There might be few shards are
hot shots. And your replication strategy
for hot shots might be a lot different
than your replication strategy for other
shards. This is the route that people
usually use. they don't use the
convoluted route that you are suggesting
that okay in this chart I will only
replicate some user and some user I will
not that's very difficult to keep a
track of very difficult to manage not a
very not a very elegant solution uh have
I made myself clear
>> yes yes
>> and and okay also like I mean sorry for
taking off so just uh like you said like
replicating DB is not a great I mean
having multiple instance like uh the way
we scale the app servers similarly like
we cannot do that for DB but like We
have an SDS concept, right? Like where
we have only one right node and like
multiple reads read nodes.
>> Yeah. So okay. So maybe you
misunderstood my statement. My statement
was more with respect to sharding. You
don't decide that I have had four shards
today and I just have 20 shards tomorrow
or I have in the next hour my number of
shards the number of partitions in which
I would I would have divided my data
increases. You can replic increase your
replicas. If your read requests are
coming becoming very high, you can
increase your replicas.
>> Does it make sense?
>> Yes.
>> But you would not want to take a
decision with respect to sharding and
increase your shards instantaneously.
Okay. So that's what my comment was.
Thank you for asking this. I hope I have
made myself clear.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thanks a lot. Okay folks. So
that's great and we have discussed a
bunch of things. I hope everybody's
happy. If somebody's not happy,
somebody's super angry at me that
Ketarun what are you teaching? You are
super slow, you are super fast or this
is not making sense. Uh I'm sorry. I
would request you to speak up and let me
know uh what you are not understanding
but do my best to make you guys
understand. Okay, cool. So let's let's
go on and discuss the next topic of
today which is the cap theorem. I will
discuss that. I will discuss space LC
and I will come back to this replication
again and discuss a bunch of more things
about replication. So I hope everybody's
excited. Let's move on to the cap
theorem. Okay, the cap theorem.
What is cap theorem? Cap theorem says in
distributed systems
you can only choose
two out of these three properties.
So I will write it down. In
distributed
systems
you can only
choose
two out of three
of these
properties. So cap has three initials. C
A P each of them represent a property
and the CAT theorem tells you that in a
system you can only choose two out of
these three properties simultaneously
okay now I will list down the properties
what does what are these properties
about uh and we have a mind readader in
our class S can read what's there in my
mind and he can just predict what I'm
going to write so uh okay Ra says my
voice is a bit muffled is that the case
with everybody. Are you not able to hear
my voice? Well,
okay, that's not the That's the case
with some people, not the case with some
people. How is that possible? Uh, let me
just check if my headphones are
connected or not. Just give me a minute.
Okay.
Uh hello folks. Is my voice better now?
Is my voice better now?
Okay. So, you should have told this to
me much earlier. I think my headphones
are not connected. So, I have these
fancy. Okay.
Rohan. Rohan. Rohan did not let me
complete my joke by saying it's the same
as before. So I had a I I thought of a
good joke to make but Rohan did not let
me complete my joke. So anyhow I hope my
voice is clear. Uh
cool cool. Uh let's let's let's go on.
Right. So cap theorem says that in
distributed systems you can only pick
two out of these three properties at the
same time. Each of these initials mean a
different property. C in the cap theorem
means consistency.
A in the cap theorem means availability
and P in the cap theorem means partition
tolerance.
Now I will explain uh these concepts as
I move along but I will take an example
first of all. Okay, this is an example
that I have been taking for years now
and you would have seen this example
being taken in a bunch of other posts or
videos also. The cap theorem example as
it's commonly called. So let me let me
repeat the theorem that in any district
you can only choose two out of these
three properties simultaneously. There
are three properties consistency,
availability, partition tolerance. You
can only select two out of these three
together. And let's take an example so
that this becomes clear. Okay. and then
I will uh give you uh what do I mean by
distributed system by distributed system
I mean any system where it's not a
single machine which is getting the job
done but a bunch of machines which are
together getting the job done right a
system in which the computation is
distributed or a system in which the
storage is distributed a system in which
you use multiple boxes to get your job
done cool now let's imagine a scenario
uh and let's Say our friend Hardep
actually builds a company, starts a
startup and that startup is a event
reminder service. Okay. So what does
that startup do? Hardep has taken a very
fancy phone number. Let's say Hardep has
taken a phone number 999911.
Let's say this is a fancy uh fancy Yeah.
Yeah. Right. right right you're right.
It's it's basically taken from a blog. I
can link the block uh to give the
correct credits. So let's say Hardep has
actually taken a very fancy number and
you can call Hardep and you can let
Hardep know of any important
event that you want Hardep to remember
for you. So, Hardep is running an event
reminder service
and they have taken a very fancy uh
phone number. So, what is the idea? The
idea is that here is our friend Hardi.
They have their diary with them. Now
people can call them
and they can tell tell us right uh they
they can tell us that let's say S called
Hardep and Sav wanted Hard to note down
that hey Sav Hardep I have a very
important event to attend so what would
you want to attend Sav uh maybe Savan
has maybe Sav has a uh
let's let's not let's not uh okay so
Maybe S wants to S wants to Okay, AB's
answer is the is the most interesting
answer. So maybe S's girlfriend is
getting married and they want to
remember the time their girlfriend is
getting married so that they can go and
attend their girlfriend's wedding. Okay.
So let's assume this is a interesting
wedding that S has to attend and S comes
and wants Hardep to register this event
that okay there is this wedding that I
need to attend. This wedding is on 700
p.m. on let's say 28th February and
please remember this for me. Okay. So
and this is a event that you have to
remember for S.
Now S might want to call Hardep back
after some time and ask Hard that hey do
you remember I told you an event to
remember for me what was that event will
go and read from their diary and tell S
that the event is that you have a
wedding coming on 28th February at 7
p.m. Is the idea clear to everybody?
What the service does? People can come
and register their events on the
service. They can call them back and
know what are the things that they have
asked you to register before. So
basically a reminder service where you
can keep things in uh in memory and then
people can come and ask you and you will
have to reply back to them. Now this is
a great service. Uh get this got popular
a lot of people started using it and
Hardep has started to make a lot of
money. Now the problem is uh what does
this fancy number do? So this fancy
number helps people to remember the
number and call Hardep easily right. So
people just call on this fancy number
and they get connected to Hardep and
Hardep answers takes a request and
answers their request. So understand
that there are two kinds of requests
coming. There's a write request and
there is a read request. The write
request is when somebody calls you and
asks you to re remember or write down a
new event. The read request is when
somebody comes to you and wants you to
answer their question and you have to
tell them what are the events that they
have. Is everybody in the class with me?
There are two kinds of request. A write
request and a read request. Now let's
say this request this this service
becomes very popular. And as this
service becomes very popular,
there are so many requests coming that
Hardy by themselves
just a single person maintaining all of
this is not possible as the number of
requests that you get are very high and
a single person is not able to keep up
with all the requests that come. Is
everybody in the class with me? Is
everybody in the class with me? Right?
So cannot handle this all by themselves.
So Hardep and their diary is no longer
sufficient. So what will do? What will
what will Hardep do? Hardep will hire
another person. Let's say Hardep hires
Nikl.
And now they have hired Nikl to work for
them. And now there are two people who
will be helping the service to remain
affluent.
Now what will happen? People will still
call on the same number.
There will be some sort of a hardware or
some sort of a load balancer or some
sort of a gateway where people connect
with connect to this gateway or this
load balancer will forward the request
randomly between Hardep or who was the
person that Hardep hired I forgot. Uh so
whosoever that person was I forgot their
name and that is the person that helps
Hadep to get this job done. Okay, it was
Nikl. So Hardep and Nikl. Now a a phone
call comes the load balancer forwards it
to anybody that person writes down and
whenever a phone call comes that person
reads the diary and let the person know
whether they have a event or not. Is
everybody able to appreciate how have
you scaled the system? Rather than
having one Hardep, you now have Hardep
and Nickel together doing this for you.
Now understand this is a distributed
system. Now you have distributed
computing, distribut distributed storage
happening. Now try and understand what
are the issues that will crop up. Right?
So let's say our friend uh show calls
and show called and said that hey I have
my girlfriend's wedding. I need to
remember this. Please remember this for
me. And the first time Ship called the
request reached her. So Shabb's request
is with Hardep and he has written what
Shib's request was about. Now next time
when Shib calls and this time randomly
this load balancer forwards Show's
request to Nikl and Show is asking Nikl
that hey man I told you to remember my
girlfriend's wedding can you please tell
me when it is? Given Nikl never wrote
that entry,
Nicl will reply back and say, "Hey, you
know what? You don't have any
girlfriend's wedding coming upcoming.
Is that is that fair enough? Do does
everybody appreciate it?" Right? So now
Shabb is told that hey there is no event
that you want me to you want me to read
from. I did not write any such event.
I'm sorry. Now show is already unhappy
that he has his girlfriend getting
wedded. But now show becomes even more
unhappy that he does not even know when
is it happening. Right? So this is a
very bad user experience. You don't even
know what you want the other people to
write. This is the scenario where your
system is not consistent. How many of
you understand this guys? The system is
not consistent.
Now let me give you the formal
definition of consistency. The formal
definition of consistency my dear
friends is
every read should return back the latest
write. So every
read
should
return back
the latest right.
Or in other words, you can define
consistency as
every machine
have the same
latest view of the truth.
How many of you understand what
consistency is? that every machine
should have the same latest view of the
of the of the machine, right? Or every
read should return back the latest
strike. Is everybody clear with the idea
of consistency? I want more people to
say yes. Is everybody clear with the
idea of consistency?
Oh, my handwriting is very poor. I I
know that s I will try and write it with
some better handwriting. Uh okay, cool.
I will I will keep that in mind. But
yeah, I want everybody in the class to
understand that right now the system is
not consistent. Is that clear? Okay, let
me rewrite the last sentence. Uh,
every
machine
has the same
latest
view
of the truth. Can you guys read the
sentence now? Manu and uh and and Savan.
Good. So every every machine has the
same latest view of the system. This is
what is called as consistency. We
understand that in this the present
state of the system, it's not
consistent. Is everybody with me? Now
what are the ways to make it consistent?
Right? What are the ways to make it
consistent? One way to make it
consistent is as follows that these
people change their way of execution.
These people change their protocol and
update their protocol to the following.
The updated protocol is
that whenever somebody calls to register
a write request,
when somebody calls to register a write
request, they don't just write it and
write it with themselves and let the
user know that hey your request is done.
They have changed the protocol. The
protocol for the right request now is as
follows
that whenever your client calls
you reach the load balancer.
The load balancer now has two people.
One is Hardib the other is Nickel.
What
you do when you have a right request is
the following
that you send a request.
When the request reaches any random
person for the right request, they note
it down the entry at their end. But they
ensure
that the entry is also written in the
other box and only after they get a
confirmation that the request is written
in the other box only then they reply
back with a with a approval that hey
your request is done. How many of you
understand this guys? So if a request
randomly reaches Hardep,
Hardep will write it at their end but
will ensure that it's written on the
other person's end as well and only
after the other person has replied back
saying that hey I have written it only
then you send an acknowledgement to the
user saying that okay your process is
done is everybody in the class with me
your write request now has to ensure
that you write on the both the systems
so that the next time When the client
calls, they can actually go to any of
the two boxes and they can get their job
done.
Is it making sense to everybody? So now
if calls the next time and no matter
whether the call gets connected to
Hardep or Nikl, they will know when
their girlfriend's wedding is. Am I
making sense to everybody in the class?
This is a system which I have four and
five interchanged. Okay, sorry. Yeah.
Four and five.
Four five. So here the system is
consistent.
Now let's understand what's the problem
with this updated protocol. Right? Uh
why is it needed to write in both the
machines? uh Nishi it's needed to it's
needed to write in both the machines
because
you want to ensure that next time
whenever the client calls no matter
wherever their call gets connected they
will get the consistent view of the
reality Nishi am I making sense that
they will get the latest
latest view of the of the reality is
this making sense to you Nishi yes uh
Hardep and Nikl are replicas is what
Karanomachi is asking yes that's true
these are replicas in a way now right so
you are replicating your information to
the other box so they are creating a
replica Muhammad asks what's three doing
three was writing the information at
your own end Muhammad does it make sense
so you added the event at your own end
am I making sense to you Mohammad three
was writing the event at your own end so
this is consistent but what's the
problem with this approach the problem
with this approach is the following
let's say
yeah yeah yeah clearly you are right but
we will come to the slow or the fast
later but there is another fundamental
issue with this approach the fundamental
issue is that you have updated your
protocol that you will only acknowledge
the right to the user that your right is
done only when you will be able to write
on both the replicas kit am I correct
but the problem is that one of these
replicas might go down for some time by
that I mean let's say nickel
has 20 off days that they have in their
company. 20 off days for the year. Right
now Nicl wants to go to Lon Navla. They
want to enjoy their time and Nikl is not
reporting to office today, right? They
want to go to Lon Navla. They want to
have their free time today. Now if Nikl
is not available today, right? If Nikl
is not available today, uh what is the
problem? Right? So if
Hardep wants everybody's girlfriend to
get married.
So Hardep can only think of those
scenarios that why will Nikl take a
leave? Because Nikl's girlfriend is now
getting married according to Hardep. No.
So let's assume Nikl is rather enjoying
in Lunavla. They want to take a day off
because they want to enjoy in Lunavla.
Now if they want to enjoy Lunavla, they
have their day off. The point is that if
nickel is not available today,
how many of you understand that even if
anybody's calling and the requests are
being routed to Hardep, Hardep will not
be able to acknowledge any new right
because the protocol says that Hardep
needs to write at their end and Nichls
and only then can send a act. How many
of you understand this that now given
the protocol what will happen?
Given the protocol
all write
requests
will fail. Am I making sense to
everybody in the class?
Is everybody in the class with me? That
all your requests write requests will
fail.
Now what is what does this mean? This
means that as a system
you are
unavailable
guys. Does it make sense? As a system
you are unavailable. Now what does
availability means? The second thing of
the cap theorem. Availability means that
you
are available
to register
requests.
In other words, availability basically
means that
whenever
queried,
you should
be able
to respond back
without
any error. Guys, am I making sense?
Availability means that whenever you are
queried, whenever you are interacted
with, you should be able to respond back
without any error.
Notice availability does not guarantee
that you are being replied with the
correct answer.
So by that I want you to understand in
the previous protocol when both of them
existed and everybody was taking their
own entries without worrying whether the
other person has taken the entry or not
the system was not consistent but the
system was still available. How many of
you understand this? In the previous
protocol when I was just writing at my
own diary,
I am not writing on my friend's diary.
So I might respond back to you with a
wrong response telling you that hey you
don't have any event. That is that is me
not being consistent but at least I was
being available. How many of you
understand that at least I was
responding to the queries that are
coming to me. Now with the updated
protocol where you ensure that you write
on the other copy before you can give an
acknowledgement to the user. Now if your
friend is unavailable, you as a system
will become unavailable because you want
to keep yourself consistent. How many of
you understand this? How many of you
understand this?
Do you start seeing a trade-off between
consistency and availability? Do you
start seeing a trade-off between
consistency and availability that either
I can ensure and I will I will complete
this the cap I will complete in some
time I will give you some more
information about it but I will repeat
this for you this is very very critical
I want everybody's attention do I have
everybody's attention in the class do I
have everybody's attention in the class
right this is very very important I want
everybody's complete attention right
nobody can be can have their attention
anywhere else right I will just sip a
sip uh sip some water and then I will
continue.
Cool. I want everybody's attention. What
I'm saying is the following.
I am teaching you cap theorem. Cap
theorem tells you that in any
distributed system you can only select
two out of the three properties
simultaneously. One property is
consistency, one property is
availability, one property is partition
tolerance. Now what is consistency?
Consistency basically means I've written
it down. Every machine has to have the
correct latest view of the reality. In
other words, every read should return
the latest write. Is everybody clear
with consistency that all the machines
that you have should have the same
knowledge, the correct knowledge of the
latest read, sorry, of the latest write.
This is consistency. What is
availability? Availability means that
whenever somebody queries something for
with you, you should be able to answer
it. You might not be giving the correct
answer but you should be able to answer
it. How many of you understand this? A
system being available means that you
should be available. Now to make more
sense out of it, I will give you an
example. Let's say how many of you have
seen YouTube videos? How many of you
have seen video YouTube videos? And how
many of you have seen that there is a
view count at the bottom of the YouTube
video. It shows you how many views the
video has had had till that point in
time. Now how many of you have also seen
the following that you see a video it
has X number of views. It has 10,242
views right now. You see the same video
after 10 minutes. You know that a bunch
of other people have seen the video in
the meanwhile, but you still see 10,240
views. How many of you have seen that
happening? That the view count of
YouTube video is not 100% accurate all
the time.
But YouTube wants to be available.
YouTube wants whenever anybody sees
their video, they should be able to tell
them the view count.
They might not be telling you the
correct view count, but they want to at
least tell you the view count. How many
of you appreciate this? How many of you
appreciate this?
Let's take another example, right? How
many of you have seen hot star playing
India Pakistan matches or India any
matches, right? Cricket matches. You see
a number of views, right? you see a
number of views uh number of people who
are live watching that that that portal
that need not be 100% accurate all the
time but what's important that hotstar
is available for you to see the view
count am I making sense hotar would
rather want to be available with respect
to the view count rather than being
consistent
and s might be looking at hotar at the
same time s might be seeing some
different view count a viewer count a
might be seeing some different viewer
count that's fine they both they both
might get a different sense of the
reality but they are at least seeing the
view count
is everybody with me is everybody does
everybody understand how availability is
different from consistency on the other
hand let's imagine a different scenario
let's imagine zerodha right so you want
to invest in a particular stock
is it fine if I show abbe that the
Reliance or let's say Adani is moving uh
moving uh vir V uh very ferociously
these days. So let's say Adani's stock
price is is 1,200 right now, right? And
somebody else when sees Adani's price on
on on on Zerodha might see a older price
of 1,800. Do you think that's
acceptable? Do you think Zerodha can say
that hey I want to be available? I
always want to tell people that Adani's
price but I can be fine with not showing
you the right price. Can Zeroda say
that? Let's imagine a banking scenario,
right? Let's imagine that you are going
to your ATM and you want to withdraw
money. Now you just deposited 1 million
rupees in your in your in your account.
You just deposited 10 lakh rupees in
your account. You go to the ATM and you
see that you only have 500 rupees in
your account. Is that fine or are you
fine with the ATM telling you please try
again later? I'm not available. Which of
the two experiences is more fine? Is the
ATM being unavailable being fine or is
the ATM being non-consistent being fine?
Right? So I hope everybody appreciates
that the ATM not being available for the
short amount of time is rather fine
rather than it not being consistent. So
I've taken a bunch of examples to
explain what consistency means, what
availability means. Is everybody with
me? Is everybody with me? I want more
yeses guys. Are you with me? Do you
appreciate what availability and
consistency are? You appreciate that. So
we took an example of a service a
reminder service that Hardep is running
and I took that example to appreciate
make you guys appreciate the difference
between consistentity. Let's redo that
example so that everybody's on the same
page. So what is this example that
Hardep is running a service people come
and call Hardep. Hardep notes down their
their their details. Whenever somebody
calls them back Hardep reads the details
and let them know about their events. If
there was a single person it's fine. Now
Hardep wants to scale. Hardep hired
another person. Now there are two people
doing the job. Hardep and Nikl. People
call. Hardep writes down. If they call
get connects connected to Hardep. People
call. If the call gets connected to
Nicl, Nikl writes down. But the problem
is if in the next subsequent call the
call gets connected to a different
person and they were only writing in
their own diary, the system will mean
will become unc inconsistent. Is
everybody with me? If you were just
writing in your own local copy, the
system is inconsistent. Guys, are you
with me? Karun Machi, I'm just going to
complete the loop. Just give me some
time. Okay, is everybody with me? That
right now the systems are inconsistent.
To make the system consistent, these
folks changed their protocol of
communication. What did they do? They
said whenever somebody calls me, I will
write it down at my entry. I will go and
write it down on the replicas entry only
when the replica returns a
acknowledgement that they have written
it only then I will acknowledge to the
user. How many of you understand the
updated protocol
right with this updated protocol how
many of you appreciate that you are
ensuring consistency that whenever
anybody calls you no matter wherever
their call gets connected they will get
the correct sense of the data because
both of them have written the correct
data at the same time. Is everybody with
me? Now you are preferring consistency.
What is the problem with this approach?
The problem with this approach is that
if for some amount of time if Nikl goes
on a lube break, right, and or Nikl goes
on a smoking break or Nikl just wanders
off and and does is is out of job for
some time, right? He is doing something
else. Now for all that time if anybody
calls and Hardep gets connected Hardep
will not be able to acknowledge the
right. Why? Because the protocol now
says that only when you write it on both
the places only then you will
acknowledge the right. If this is the
protocol I want everybody in the class
to appreciate that you are being not
available at that time. Is everybody
with me? You are not available at that
time.
Now let's try to solve this as well.
Let's try to solve this as well. We
update our protocol slightly. Our
updated protocol is as follows.
Uh Manu wants a short break. Manu let me
complete my cap theorem then maybe we
can have a short break. Right? Or uh
guys the class is a 3-hour long class.
Is that correct? The class is a
three-hour long class. Usually I I have
seen if I'm not wrong takes classes even
higher than 3 hours, right? Uh even even
longer than 3 hours. So it's a 3-hour
long class. So we'll end at 12. A lot of
you are saying 11:30. Why do you want
me? Why do you want the class to end by
11:30? We are discussing a lot more
details than what's required. So I am
teaching you things which are not even
required. Right? So let's not cut the
class time short, right? Okay. So I will
finish by 11:45 or so. Okay. I will
finish by 11:45 or so. Uh and then maybe
I will complete I will take questions
later. Okay. Cool. Cool. Now uh
Basiah says please finish by 1:30. I am
sure Basiah did not mean that they
wanted 11:30 but they have given me a
time limit till 1:30. Okay Basaya I will
finish by 1:30.
Just joking right? So let's continue.
The updated protocol is as follows. The
updated protocol is that now uh if
nickel is on a leave,
if nickel is on a leaf, what Hardep will
rather do is as follows.
This is Hardep. This is Nikl.
You have a load balancer. Clients call
you. Our friend Nicl is on a leave to
Lunavla. They are on leave. They are not
in office today.
So what will the updated protocol look
like? It will look like as follows. That
in cases when nickel is unavailable,
in cases where nickel is unavailable,
I will only write down to myself
and reply an acknowledgement without
worrying about nickel.
When nickel is unavailable, I will take
the information only with me.
And this is fine because if somebody
calls and nickel is unavailable, the
call is anyhow going to come to Hardi.
How many of you understand this? The
call is anyhow going to come to Hardi
because Nicl is anyhow unavailable.
But when tomorrow morning nikl comes
back,
I will call them early in the office and
I will ensure that all the pending
entries I had at my end.
Whenever they come back, I will
off in an offline later manner, I will
sync up those entries with Nikl. How
many of you understand this?
and I will in an offline fashion sync
those entries with nickel and once they
are back up
they will also have those entries and
now if anybody calls anybody there will
be no inconsistency. How many of you
appreciate this? How many of you
appreciate this?
That if nickel is unavailable
I only write entries at my end.
Given nickel is unavailable, people are
only going to reach to me
and I will be able to answer to their
queries.
Now before nickel comes back up, I will
ensure that they note down my entries
which are pending only at my end so that
we become consistent the moment they are
back up. Anybody who calls now will get
the correct understanding of the state.
How many of you understand this my dear
friends? How many of you understand this
ra you can store these entries in any
sort of a queue in any sort of a
database and call them pending and then
run a chron job get this synced up okay
Raab does that answer your question I
hope it does how many of you understand
this my dear friends how many of you
understand this I will quickly repeat it
for Dhj's idea is that when my nickel is
unavailable I will only write down
entries at my end will not become
unavailable for my for my friends for my
users
I will only write down the entry at my
end. Whenever they call back, I will
read the entry to them and I'm fine. But
before Nikl comes back up, I will write
my copy pending entries to them so that
whenever they are back, we are all
consistent. Is everybody in the class
with me? D are you with me? That I am
ensuring that we are consistent before
they start serving traffic. Okay. In
this scenario, how many of you see that
your system is both consistent
and your system is both available? It's
both available and consistent. How many
of you understand this my dear friends?
How many of you understand this?
Is everybody with me? If Harp is also
down Satyendra uh then the system will
be unavailable. But that's a case where
everything is on fire. But if there is a
system require who can respond to your
queries, they will be responding to
queries. Is that correct Satendra?
Availability means if there is a system
out there, they should be able to
respond to your queries. If your entire
data center is on fire, then that's a
different scenario. Okay, Satyendra, I
hope that makes sense. So in this
scenario, it's both available and
consistent. I hope there is no
confusion.
But this is where the third part of the
cap theorem becomes interesting. GAP
theorem says that you can only pick
three out of two out of these three
things together. Consistency,
availability, partition tolerance. So we
are seeing a system where it's both
consistent and available. But let me
tell you where the trick lies. Now what
is partition tolerance? Before that is
everybody with me till this point in
time? Is everybody with me? This is now
the very interesting thing that's very
important for you to grasp now comes.
Okay. So what is partition tolerance?
Before that what is partition?
Partition basically means a network
partition.
Now what is a network partition?
A network partition is a scenario where
two machines
tell me if there are two machines
talking to each other how will they
talk? They will talk over a network. Am
I correct?
How am I interacting with you guys? I am
interacting with you guys over a network
which is the internet. Whatever bytes
are coming from my machine are going to
your machine over a network called the
internet. Is that correct? Now imagine
if you are a machine and I am in a
machine in the same data center. Our
communication will happen over a
internet but again a network. So two
machines always communicate over a
network. Is that correct? they always
communicate over a network. Network
partition basically means that due to
some reason the connectivity between the
two machines is down for some time. So
network partition
network partition means that this
network is broken temporarily.
How many of you understand this? How
many of you understand this?
that the network is broken.
It does not mean that this machine is
broken from everybody else in the world.
All I am saying that the network between
M1 and M2, the communication channel
between machine one and machine 2 is
broken for some time. It does not mean
that machine 2 cannot communicate with
anybody else. It does not machine that
machine one cannot communicate with
anybody else. They might be able to
communicate with everybody else in the
world but the network between M1 and M2
is temporarily down. How many of you
understand this guys? what I what I mean
by network partition the word partition
and I uh and don't confuse this
partition with with sharding or or
replication
right network partition basically means
network partition basically means that
the network is broken
akil my dear friend partition can mean
two different things in data
partitioning and network partitioning
right now I'm talking about partition
which means network partition. Guys, are
you with me? Is everybody in the class
with me? Is everybody in the class with
me? Network partition basically means
that two machines right now cannot talk
to each other because the network is
broken between these two machines.
In the example that I was discussing,
let's assume Harib and Nikl had a fight.
The P in scap is partitioning. It's
basically partition tolerance. I'm going
to come to that show. But let's go come
back to the example. Let's assume Nikil
and Hardep had a fight. How many of you
have seen Taraka Gulishma?
So do you remember there was a there was
a there was a character in Tarakishma
called Natukaka. So for those who have
not seen it's not important. I'm just
trying to make people laugh, right? So
maybe you can just fake laugh. Okay. So
there was a partition called Natukaka.
There was a there was a character called
Natukaka who always kept on asking for a
raise. That character always kept on
asking
always kept on asking for a raise that
hey please raise my salary. Please raise
my salary. Now let's assume our friend
Nikl was asking for a raise and Hardep
did not accept that request and now
these two guys have had a fight. They're
not talking to each other. Nat Gaga is
not talking to the sage gi. Okay. So
let's assume that these two folks are
not talking to each other. They are they
are they are ignoring each other. Now if
they are not talking to each other, this
is what I want you to appreciate with
network partitioning that there's a
network between these two folks and the
network is broken. How many of you
appreciate my example? My stupid little
example that the network between the two
machines is broken. Right? If the
network between the two machines is
broken, there is where the problem will
come. And before I before I go there,
before I go there, the reality of the
world is that network partition can
always happen. How many of you will
vouch for that? No matter how good a
connection you have, you trying to
connect to the video call and not being
able to do that for some time. Does that
happen? Does that happen? That happens
all the time. No matter how good on a
connection you have, you will always
have scenarios where network will
partition, where network will be
unavailable. Guys, am I making sense to
everybody? Network is always unreliable.
Unreliable. You might have read this
statement multiple times. Network
is always
unreliable. Have you read this statement
before my dear friends? Network is
always unreliable. So you can always
have a scenario where a network
partition happens and when a network
partition happens, this is where cap
theorem comes in full force. Now imagine
our second updated protocol was that
Hardep was writing the entries and Nikl
was out of office. Whenever Nikl comes
back up, Hadep makes sure that Nikl
writes those entries and then both of
them are consistent and available.
Everything is honky dory. But if at that
time when the sync was happening a
network partition happens
do you understand that the system will
become inconsistent?
How many of you understand this
if at the time of syncing up the network
gets partitioned the system will become
inconsistent.
Right? So in the real world,
Capum tells you that you will only be
able to select two out of these three
options. You can either be consistent,
available, partition tolerant. Only two
of these three things can be together.
The third thing, the P in part cap
theorem stands for partition tolerance.
Right?
Now it's a word play of English and even
though it's very easy for me to
appreciate but I somehow find it very
strange that some people don't
understand the word play partition is a
is a negative thing thing right a
partition happened a connection broke
between two machines partition tolerance
basically means that your system as a
whole is allowed to have partitions it
is tolerant to partitions Guys, does it
make sense? If it does not make sense to
you, forget the word tolerance. It's
just a word play. If it does not make
sense to you, forget it. Basically, CAPM
tells you that you can either be
partition tolerant, available, and out
of these consistent available and
partition tolerant, you can only be two
things at the same time. Which means
that only if the system will not have
partitions only then you can be
consistent and available at the same
time. How many of you understand this?
Only if the system will not have
partitions only then you will have you
will be consistent and and available.
But the problem is that the reality of
the world is that network is always
unreliable
which means that it's impossible to
build a system where network partition
network partition tolerance is not
required. So in a way the essential
choice becomes between either you are
consistent and partition tolerant or you
are available or partition tolerant. How
many of you understand this?
How many of you understand this?
In distributed systems
partition tolerance is always required.
Why? Because network is always
unreliable
which means that you can either be
consistent and partition tolerant or you
can be available or partition tolerant.
Now some of you will have a very
interesting question that
how then why did you frame the law
accordingly? Why did you frame the
theorem accordingly? Why did you not say
it's CP or AP? Right? You might have
this question. So to answer that let me
give you the answer that if you had a
single machine you did not have two
machines talking to each other. Do you
understand then partition tolerance is
not required because network is not even
involved. If you have a single machine
then no network is involved. If Hardep
did not even hire Nikl. If Hardep was
handling it all by himself, then you can
say that the single machine
given that no network is involved, a
single machine can be both consistent
and available at the same time. Guys, is
this making intuitive sense to
everybody? Is this making intuitive
sense to everybody? Is everybody happy?
Are you guys smiling? Does this make
sense? Is this is this a beautiful
thing? Right? Are we able to appreciate
the beauty of the system design world?
Right? This is a topic that is going to
be tested in your high level design
interviews all the time. And if you
understand this well, you're going to do
great at least in that portion of your
HLD interviews. Guys, am I making sense?
Is only 15 are only 15 people happy? I
hope everybody's happy. What I'm saying
is that only in case when you have a
single machine, if a single machine is
there, there is no requirement for a
network over which you will communicate.
Am I making sense? If there's a single
machine, there is no requirement for you
to have a network over which you will
communicate. If there is no network
because there is a single machine, there
is no network partition tolerance which
is required. Am I making sense?
Rahul, you are right. Uh basically, it's
a word play only. uh what I'm
essentially trying to tell you is that
only if a single machine is there only
then you can have both consistency and
availability at the same time. Rahul am
I making sense? Rahul Kash am I making
sense? Only when you have a single
machine running only then you can be
consistent available at the same time
otherwise partition tolerance is a given
and hence you always have to choose
between consistency or availability. Is
everybody in the class with me? Is
everybody in the class with me?
Now uh Akash has raised raised a hand.
Akash Akash I will unmute you. Rahul you
also have a doubt I will unmute you as
well and if there is any other person
who has doubts I will unmute you one by
one but before that let me complete my
thought right and then I will unmute you
guys. Is that fine? Let me complete my
thought right. My thought that I wanted
to complete here is the following that
let's imagine this example once again
and understand the cap theorem in its
full beauty. Right? So you have a
client.
Your client reaches out to your load
balancer.
Your load balancer has multiple boxes
running.
Now what I'm trying to tell you is the
following. that one option was that they
both were writing individually and they
were not sharing notes. So let me write
it down. Option one
both
writing
separately
no node sharing.
If both are writing separately and
there's no note sharing happening then
the system is not consistent. Is
everybody in the class with me?
This is one option that your system is
not consistent. Your system will be
available.
Am I making sense? And your system of
course can tolerate partitions because
if Nikl and Hardep are not talking to
each other we are all fine. Yes Koshik
even inside a data center the network is
always unreliable. The network is always
unreliable. Does that make sense Koshik?
I hope it does. So the system in this
example when they are taking the
individual nodes and not talking to each
other it's not consistent. It's
available and of course it's partition
tolerant
that even if they don't talk we are
fine. So what is this system my dear
friends? This system is AP. How many of
you understand this? This system is
available and partition tolerant. I want
everybody in the class to answer. Is
this making sense? This is making sense.
The option B that you had.
Rahul, I will repeat it. Rahul, do you
mind if I unmute you? Let me unmute you.
Explain this to you and every and to
everybody in the class. Rahul, can I
unmute you? Yes. So, let me unmute
Rahul. Please speak up, my dear friend.
Let's understand it together.
Akash you as well. Hey Rahul. Hi. So
Rahul what I was saying is that the
first option is that these people are
not sharing note with each other.
Whenever a call comes they write it down
in their own system and whenever a call
comes they read from the system and
answer it. Rahul is it making sense that
there is no note sharing happening
between the two people. Rahul are you
with me?
Hello.
Okay. Okay. So, Rahul went away. I hope
this is clear to everybody that there is
no note sharing happening. The problem
with is this is that if somebody else
not noted down the request and now the
read request comes to somebody else, you
will present a wrong reality. You will
return back with a wrong answer. Right?
So, in this the system was not
consistent, it was available. It was
partition problem. The second option
that you have is that there is node
sharing happening.
Right?
No sharing happening
and
write
will only be acknowledged
when
both copies have it. How many of you
understand the option B that the right
will only be acknowledged when both
copies have it? In this kind of a
scenario, I want everybody in the class
to answer this for me. The system is of
course partition tolerant because if
these two folks don't talk to each other
for some time, we are fine. The system
will always be consistent in this
because you are only writing when both
of them can write it. But the system is
not available because you might have a
scenario where if one of our two friends
are down, the entire system will be
down. Is everybody in the class with me?
So this is a system which is consistent
and partition tolerant. I want everybody
in the class to answer this guys. Are
you with me?
You are with me. That's great. The third
option. How is it partition tolerant?
Hard because even when these two folks
don't talk to each other,
you as a system are still functioning.
the read requests that come to you, you
will still be able to respond to them,
right? So, partition tolerance basically
means that the partition can happen. You
are allowing the partition to happen. Of
course, the partition can happen. It
will always happen. You are allowing for
the partition to happen. Gardep, are you
with me? Partition tolerance is a given,
right? The third option that you have is
that The third option that you have is
you
write at both places.
But when
one machine
is down,
you only write
on the remaining machine. So when one
machine is dying down, you only write on
the remaining machine. You write at both
the places, but when one machine is
down, you only write at the remaining
machine. And
before
the down machine comes back up,
you sink.
Is everybody in the class able to
understand this?
Before the down machine comes back up,
you sink, right? And you always remain
available to take the rights. In this
scenario my dear friends you will be
available all the time.
You having to account for partition is
always the requirement.
The problem is at the time of syncing if
your partition happened then your system
will not be consistent. Is everybody in
the class with me? Is everybody in the
class with me? So your system is
essentially going to be available
and partition tolerant.
Is everybody in the class with me? Is
everybody in the class with me? So I
hope I have made myself clear that your
system can either be available and
partition tolerant or consistent
partition tolerant. I will unmute a
bunch of folks who want to be unmuted
now. Akash I have unmuted you. Anybody
else wants to be unmuted? Please raise
your hand and then I move ahead move. Uh
hey Akash, please tell me.
>> Yeah. Hi Tun, am I audible?
>> Yeah, you're audible. Please tell me.
Yeah, I wanted to talk about the single
machine where you said that both
consistent like all of the three can be
achieved
>> right all of the two can be achieved in
a single machine when you have a single
machine partition partition tolerance is
not even required it's irrelevant
because there is no partitioning network
partitioning that can happen there is a
single machine you don't talk to any
other machine that you need partition
tolerance for and hence your system can
be consistent and available
>> correct yeah so partitioning is Not even
there. Not even a concern.
>> Yeah. Not not not even a not even a
possibility because there is a single
machine, right?
>> But here uh the problem that I see is
that if my that machine is down, I am
not available.
>> If that machine is down, then you're not
available. You are right. But in that
scenario, you can say that let's say I
have a 100 machines. If I am the funky
one and I take a matchbox and I put my
entire data center on fire, then you can
say that hey, my Facebook is not
available. Of course that can happen. If
there is a single machine that is down,
then there is no point of availability.
Right? If there are 100 machines and all
of them are down, there is no point of
availability. Availability basically
means that if there is a machine alive
to take your request and somebody
reaches out to you, you are able to
respond back to them. So in the cap
theorem world, the availability means
this that if there is a machine that you
take your request, you should be
available to respond back. You should be
able to respond back. Am I making sense?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay.
>> When you talk about a system being
available overall, then of course from a
user perspective, if you irrespective
whether the machines are up or not, you
are as a system available or not to the
to the user if the user is able to
communicate to you or not. But from a
cap theorem perspective, we are talking
from an idea that if there is a machine
ready to take your request, you should
always be able to take it. You should
not be in a scenario that the machine is
up but you should say that hey I cannot
take your request because something else
is down. So in option B what was
happening is that Hardep was there to
take request but Hadep could not take
them because the protocol suggested that
he cannot take it unless and until the
other person takes it. So that was not
available from a capturum perspective.
Does that make sense Akash?
>> Yes. Got it. Thank you so much.
>> Okay. Thanks a lot Akash. Thanks a lot.
Anybody else has any question? Anybody
else has any question? Please raise your
hand. Uh rather than reading through all
the comments, it's easier for me to hear
you out and then answer you. Sor has a
question. Hey Sor, please tell me.
Runali, I have admitted you as well. If
you have a question,
>> Masaya, please don't ask for breaks. You
want me to end the class early as well
and break as well. Then I will have to
cut on the content. I really can't do
that. So please, please, please drink
water while I'm answering questions.
Anybody who wants to take a break, take
a break for a minute or two. I'm
answering some questions and then we
proceed. Okay.
>> Yeah. Hey Sor please tell me. Hi.
>> So when system two that is n comes
available
>> he will come available using some
network. Why can't uh the first system
use that network to sync up
>> right? So okay so you I did not get your
question. He will become unavailable
using a network. By unavailable I mean
that your system is not available. the
system is down. The machine may be
restarted. The machine had some issue
and it's not functioning for some time.
That the system is not there for some
time. This is what non not available
basically means. Does it make sense?
That the system is not there for some
time. Am I making sense? That
>> the system restarted. The system went
out of power. The system had some issue.
So not being available basically means
that the system is not there for the
time being. Okay.
>> Yep. So my question is on option C means
third partition to inside.
>> So at some point when it becomes
available
>> right?
>> So it will interact with gateway using
some network only.
>> Okay. Got it. Got it. So when it becomes
unavail when it becomes available it
will communicate with the gateway or the
load balancer. That's fine. It was
communicating with machine one as well.
This is fine. But what can happen is
that the machine one and machine two.
The network only between machine one and
machine two broke. The box nickel is
still able to communicate with load
balancer but it's not able to
communicate with the other machine. So
this can always happen. You can always
have a scenario when you are not able to
communicate with a particular machine. A
network partition happened with a
particular machine. This is what I'm
talking about sort of. Does it make
sense? So what will happen? you are not
able to sync up your your repending
requests to Nickel but nickel is still
able to take requests from the load
balancer. So calls can start coming to
Nickel but you are not able to sync up
your data with Nickel. Okay.
>> Okay. So at that time if they use
different network or we can have
multiple network but
>> it's not only a problem when they use
different networks try to understand
that all of this might be wires between
them right they might be on a same
network and all of them are connected
using wires they transmit their data
across wires now there might be a
scenario that this particular wire is
broken or there might be a scenario that
the port somehow or some packets get
dropped the packets that you were
transferring they get dropped network is
always unreliable By I by that we mean
that there are a bunch of different
possibilities that can happen so that
the communication channel between two
machines is broken for some time. Okay.
There can be a 100 different things that
can happen from a network perspective
that you are unavailable to talk to this
particular machine at this particular
time.
Does it make sense?
>> Makes sense. Yes. Makes thanks.
>> Thanks a lot. Thanks a lot. Surali
your turn.
>> Uh hi Ton. It was almost same question
from me. Uh in option C again if you
scroll it down a little bit.
>> Sure. Sure. Yeah. Please tell me.
>> So here I was asking same like if if you
are saying the person is not available
and once he is available we can sync the
data. Right.
>> Right.
>> But then how then it's
>> right. So when when they are available
you sync the data but at that time
if while you are syncing or before you
could sync there was a partition
tolerant there was a partition that
happened a network partition that
happened now the sync could not get
completed right the idea here is that I
took a simplified example where I
assumed them to be people now maybe it's
difficult for you to imagine that oh the
nickel came back to work and I'm not
able to talk to them so that's why I
gave you an example that they're not
talking to each other. Right? So that's
it's difficult to imagine that people
are not talking to each other. But in
systems try to understand that there is
a possibility that the connection using
which they are talking is broken
temporarily. They are not able to sync
with each other.
>> Hardep is not we have not asked Hardep
to take a pause and say I'm not
available. Hardep is still available.
Hardep is still answering questions.
Hardep is still communicating. But the
problem is that the channel between
Harib and Nicl is broken. So when Har is
not stopping, Nikl came back up. The
load balancer knows Nickel is back. Load
will start sending requests to Nickel.
But the channel between me and Har and
Nickel is broken. The sync up could not
get completed. So the probability of you
being inconsistent is there because
because of network partition your
consistency could not be achieved.
>> Okay. If you wanted to assure
consistency, you should have made Hardep
unavailable. He would have he should
have only acknowledged a right only when
he himself has seen that the other
person has noted it down. Right. So
that's the point.
>> Yes. Got it. Now,
>> okay. Thank you, Munali. Is there any
other question? Anybody else has any
other question?
Okay, Vishal, I understand your comment.
I will not stretch the class beyond
11:45. I promise you that. Is that a
fair promise, my dear friend? Maybe not
11:30, 11:45. Okay. 11:45. 11:45ish.
I will try and complete the class. Hey
Rahul, please tell me.
>> I don't know.
>> Yeah, tell me. So I think pretty much uh
it makes sense the option one and two
which is um
>> u CA and CA and AP sorry CB and AP
>> okay
>> again uh when we say that uh it's not
practically possible to have a C
environment then why theorem
>> and to sorry to have a to have a CA to
have CA right because it's only possible
if you have a single machine there's no
network involved
>> yeah But uh cap theorem necess I mean
that is in like that is for distributed
systems in the first place right?
>> You're right. Oh,
>> so try to understand it this way Rahul
my friend that imagine that there is a
distributed system right it has a bunch
of functionalities you have multiple
machines doing multiple computations
simultaneously it's a disute system but
try to understand there might be a
special use case in your system where
for that use case you have a single
machine so what we are talking is on a
use case basis is on a subsystem basis
subsection bas cases your entire system
might be distributed but for one
particular use case you wanted
desperately consistency and availability
to be true all the time and hence you
had a single machine so imagine it this
way so do you do you understand that
understand that the entire system might
be distributed
>> I I understand that in theory but I do
not understand that as probably if you
can give me an example where
>> for sure CA yeah where CA would be uh as
an
>> so let's let's let's understand an
example
Let's assume that there is a very uh
there is a use case where you not have a
lot of traffic for a particular use
case. So let's let's imagine uh some
something very specific. Let's say there
are a 100,000 people in your
organization and you have a bunch of
different systems to manage your people
in the organization. Now for one
particular request which is a very rare
event and does not affect a lot of
people let's say there is a employee in
my organization that is doing something
fish and I want to block their access
right I want to block their access I
don't want them to be I I want to
blacklist them right it can be an
employee it can be a user it can be
something if I want to blacklist
somebody for that particular use case I
want to be sure that I am available all
the time if I want to blacklist somebody
immediately I must be able to do it. It
should not be the case that my service
of blacklisting is unavailable at this
point in time.
>> At the same time it also must be
consistent that I should not be the it
should not be the scenario that hey I
have blocked somebody but they are still
able to access some parts of my network.
Are you making are you able to
appreciate it for a very special use
case in my ecosystem I want my system to
be both consistent and available. But
then yeah, sure.
>> What will I maybe do is I will maybe
have a SQL box where I will ensure that
I have I have a list of blacklisted
users and I will be going I will be
passing through whenever somebody
authenticates I would be passing through
that box list. So a single SQL box gives
you a lot of asset transactions
guarantees right. It gives you
guarantees.
>> Yeah. I I mean see we have consistency
we have availability in this scenario
>> right
>> how but how are we getting rid of P in
this case
>> we're not getting rid of P in this case
we are compromising we are compromising
on the on the on the scale of the system
we are compromising on the scalability
of the system we are saying that we will
run a single machine to get this job
done I will maybe invest a lot more
money to buy a single machine that can
handle all of this so I am compromising
on my distributed nature for this
particular use case and hence I'm saying
yeah
>> yeah I mean my my question was that only
like uh a scenario where consistency and
availability is there but we are not
able to achieve P because basically in a
nutshell what cap is only two out of the
three things can function A I get it CP
I get it
>> got it got it so what what you want to
essentially ask is the following that
hey Tarun I am getting C and A I'm not
able to achieve partition tolerance can
you please explain it to me right yeah
>> so what I am I I've already explained
that but I will have to reword it
because it's a word play at the end of
the day
>> what I want to essentially tell you is
that when you say that your system is
both consistent and available
>> but not
it means you are making your system
intolerant to partitions
>> how
>> which means that when your system has a
partition
this proposition that you are both
consistently available is going to be
unachievable
So you are saying that to be consistent
and available at the same time I want to
give a guarantee that partitions will
not happen because I am being intolerant
to partitions and being intolerant to
partitions in a system where you have
multiple machines is not possible
because network are never reliable which
means that you are enforcing yourself in
a box and saying that I will only have
one box only then I can have consistent
availability at the same time because I
am choosing not to have partition
tolerance if I'm choosing not to have
partition tolerance it means I cannot
have more than one box am I making sense
because partition tolerance is always
required in a multibbox system is that
making sense Rahul
>> so when you say that
>> so it's a word play let me let me
complete it because uh no matter how
much of a back and forth you do unless
and until you appreciate the word play
this will not become clear I understood
your question your question is that hey
Tarun tell me an example or try to make
me appreciate that partition tolerance
is being compromised when you want a CA
system. Right? So try to understand that
partition tolerant. The word partition
tolerant basically means that you are
tolerant to partitions in a way. You are
allowing. Yeah. Let me complete because
uh let let me be very frank. No matter
how much of a back and forth you do
unless until I get my point across, you
will not be able to understand it. So
let me try and get my point across. So
what I'm saying Rahul is that you are
being tolerant to partitions basically
means that you are allowing for
partitions to happen. Okay. In any
system where you have more than one
machines where those machines are
communicating over network partitions
can always happen. And when partitions
happen and you still have a system in
place, it means the moment you have more
than one machines, you have to accept to
the fact that you have to be tolerant to
partitions.
Okay Rahul, so you have to be tolerant
to partitions only then only when you
give that give give in to that fact only
then you can have multiple machines. Now
if you have multiple machines you cannot
be more consistent and available at the
same time. You have to choose between
one of them. So what I am essentially
trying to put forward is that if you
want to be consistent available at the
same time, you'll have to let go of the
possibility of partitions happening.
Yeah. Which is only possible if you had
a single machine.
>> Yeah. Uh I I I just want to end with one
quick example. Won't want to take a lot
of time. Um I'll give you an example.
You please suggest me whether this is a
right example or not. So I have a system
uh I uh I have a system where in I need
multiple uh multiple computer systems or
basically I do need a network. I do need
multiple servers but but uh I'm but the
the more priority of my system is to be
consistent and available. So what I'm
doing is I'm I'm getting rid of that
those extra servers because my priority
is C and A over partitioning. So I'll
say that okay I'll I'm I'm I'm happy
with the slow slow speed of my system.
Let me get rid of 10 servers. I'll just
keep one server so that I can make sure
that it is CLA. Although I will get rid
of partitioning and in that case uh the
downside is I I'm getting slow speed but
but I'm choosing CNA.
>> What you are saying is absolutely
correct Rahul but then you will always
have to have a single box because
partitions are not because partitions
are not predictable. you you you won't
even know that you are having a
partition and you are having a partition
>> right so the point is
>> so what you suggested is absolutely
correct what you suggested that hey to
be considered available I will let go of
other machines and only run a single
machine which is fine which is fine what
I have to tell you is that you cannot
predict and beforehand prepare yourself
to let go of machines
>> you will have to build a system which is
running on a single machine it's
consistently available all the time you
have the guarantee but you are not even
allowing for partitions to happen and
you do that by not having multiple
machines.
>> Okay, you're on the same page. That's
that's very h that's a very happy thing
to uh very happy state to be in. Cool. I
will now take more questions later. I
hope people in the class are broadly
with me. They are able to understand the
cap theorem. You can only select two out
of these three properties at the same
time. This is called as cap theorem.
Right? In any distributed system, you
will have to either choose consistency,
availability, partition tolerance, two
out of these three. And usually whenever
you have more than one machines,
partition tolerance is a given. The
system actually becomes CA sorry CP or
AP. Is everybody with me? I want
everybody to say yes. Say yes. Right.
Hardep. I will give you a bunch of
practical examples and you will help me
answer them. Right? You will help me
answer them. And while designing the
systems, we will discuss them in our in
our classes where we uh do system
designing and the groundup. there I will
tell you how to take that tradeoff what
to do what not to do to make a system
consistent or available okay that's
great we are on the same page everything
is going great now I want to take you to
the next theorem which is a pace
uh uh okay so which is the pelick
theorem uh yes any system will fall into
this okay my dear friend
uh yes in our project module we are
going to see this practically as So
let's look at the next theorem
which is more of a
extension to the cap theorem. So just
for the kind of questions that our
friend Rahul was asking or the kind of
doubts that you guys might have had this
is the reason why people actually
extended the cap theorem and started
using the pace LC theorem. Essentially
it's the same thing but just gives you
one more attribute to think about and I
want everybody's attention. Pace LC
theorems means the following
that it says the following that whenever
partition happens you have to choose
between availability or consistency. So
the pack in the pace LT theorem is
basically a inversion of cap right. So
what it says is
whenever
partition happens
choose between
availability
or consistency.
In other words, while designing the
system, you have to keep into mind that
partitions will happen and at the time
when partitioning is happening, your
system would either want to be
consistent or would want to be
available. Am I with is is everybody in
the class with me? Am I clear? So just
like in this scenario unless and until
the scenario that okay uh my other
friend is I am not I am not fighting
with Hardib is not in a fight with with
with with with Nikil then you can still
assume that you are for now both
consistent available but whenever fight
happens you you will have to have had a
protocol such that either consistency is
preferred or availability is preferred.
Is everybody in the class with me? Is
everybody in the class with me? So base
LC theorem is uh I will replace the word
whenever and I will rather say if
partition happens. So whenever or let's
use both the words
whenever partition happens choose
between availability or consistency. So
the P A C and PLC mean this P means
whenever partition happens either you
have to choose availability or
consistency. Is everybody in the class
with me? Is everybody in the class with
me? Is everybody in the class with me?
Right. The ELC in the pace LC theorem. I
will now tell what ELC mean. So PSC is
basically just just the cap theorem that
whenever partition is happening your
protocol would either prefer consistency
or would prefer availability. ELC
basically means something else and that
I will complete here. else.
In the else part, we essentially want to
convey that when
partition is not happening. And my dear
friends, whenever I use the word
partition in the cap theorem, I mean
network partition. Is that clear to
everybody in the class? Whenever I use
the word partition in in CAP theorem or
PCPLC,
I mean network partition. It's a given.
So else when the partition is not
happening.
So this E stands for else
and LC stands for latency or
consistency. So when the partition is
not happening then you choose between
latency
or consistency.
And I had somebody in the class point
this out in the example as well right.
Uh yeah that's great Rahul. Maybe we
were not able to understand each other
and hence we took the time to come to
the same conclusion. We are at the at
the same conclusion at the end but we
would just want maybe there was some
communication gap. Cool. So now whenever
the partition is not happening then you
have to in a way choose between latency
or consistency. I will explain it to you
with the same example. So my dear
friends, when these guys were talking to
each other, when these guys were talking
to each other, do you remember
that Hardep had to write the entry on
Nickel's end as well before
acknowledging to the user? Guys, are you
with me?
You had to ensure that the right is
maintained on Nickel's end as well. How
many of you understand that doing this
will introduce latency? How many of you
understand that doing this will
introduce latency?
Right? So if you want a system which is
highly consistent then you are in a way
compromising with your latency. Your
latency shoots up.
On the other hand, if you want a system
to be very very low latency then you
will have to compromise or on immediate
consistency. How many of you understand
this guys? I will draw a diagram to
summarize the pace LC theorem and then I
will move into the deeper woods and
explain to you. So many more things that
will make you feel a lot more confident.
Is everybody ready? Right. So let me
draw a diagram and then I will move
deeper into the words discuss as many
things as possible and then move to the
next topic. Right. Yeah Satya that's
right. So let me write it down. Draw a
diagram.
So whenever the partition happens
and that will happen anytime
you have to choose between availability
or consistency.
Does everybody in the class appreciate
this? Whenever the partition happens
you'll have to choose between
availability or consistency. I want
everybody in the class to appreciate
this.
Whenever the partition is not happening
in the else part, you have to either
have a system
with very low latency
or you can choose a system with very
high consistency.
How many of you are with me? You can
either choose a system uh basically in
the usual scenario your consistency is
also
uh against notion of latency right and I
will explain latency. Latency basically
means the time it takes for your request
to be completed. motion. Does it make
sense? In the example, if you have to
write your same qu query, same request
to the other person as well, your user
will have to wait for some time before
your request is taken in. Am I correct
my dear friend Bian? So your latency for
the user is going to be compromised.
So you have to either choose between low
latency or high consistency. Am I clear
to you my friend Karum Karum Karumanchi
that either your latency needs to be
either you can support very low latency
or you can support very high
consistency. I will give you an example.
I want everybody in the class to
understand this example. Uh when you try
and book a Tatkal ticket on IRCTC
have you tried booking a Tatkal ticket
on IRCTC?
You have right? Or have you tried if
you've not tried booking a if you are
those one of those uh super rich
individuals who say that hey you know
what I never go via trains. I have lived
a life where I never had to go via
trains. I always booked flight tickets.
If you're one of those then you would
have tried booking flight tickets right?
You would have tried tried booking
flight tickets. While you try a book
flight ticket or you book a car ticket,
do you notice that when even when you
have pressed enter that hey please book
it for me.
Do you see do you see that there is a
time lag between when you request and
after some time it comes back to you
with a response that hey here is your
P&R number your seats are booked. How
many of you have seen that? How many of
you have seen that that there is a
latency there is a high latency between
the time you book and it actually gets
booked.
So given
these folks want the system to be highly
available. Is everybody with me? They
can't allow two people to same the book
the same car ticket right sorry they
want the system to be highly consistent.
They want the system to be highly
consistent which means that they will
have to sacrifice with their latency.
The time it takes to get this done is
going to be higher. How many of you
understand this? How many of you
understand this?
The time it takes to get this request
registered is higher. Okay. So you
cannot have a system which is super low
latency which happens immediately and at
the same time is highly consistent.
Okay.
Okay. Got it. Got it. Got it. Got it. So
Ajit is confused and that's that's
that's right. Ajit and everybody else in
the class. How many of you have wrongly
understood this else part to be the
scenario where your system is on a
single machine? How many of you have
misunderstood this? How many of you are
imagining this else part to be there
when the system is on a single machine?
That's not what I'm doing. I'm saying
something else. I want everybody's
attention again a and everybody else do
I have everybody's attention please hear
to this again right so one thing before
I even answer that so I can conduct this
class in a lot quicker manner
in a manner where you will not even
realize that you have doubts and you
will go back home and you will realize
that you had doubts in the interview
itself that will be very easy for me to
conduct that will make you very happy
that there are no doubts and you to go
back home but you will not you would
have not even understood the reality of
the topic. I am taking extra pain to
make this system the make this topic a
lot more tougher for you than somebody
else would have taught but I'm doing
this with the purpose that you
understand things at a lot fundamental
level are you guys able to appreciate
that I am purposefully making a system
single simple thing difficult so that
you don't miss out on anything there is
no blind spot for you you understand
things way better right so appreciate
that that we are taking the extra pain
we are making it extra difficult so that
we understand it better you can cover
this content in one hour and and go back
home uh and you would not even realize
that there are doubts that you had right
so don't worry we are doing it the tough
way but we are doing it the right way
okay so now let me repeat what the doubt
I saw in Ajit's question right Ajit's
question was that hey Taran I whenever
the else part I imagined it to be on a
single system because you yourself were
telling me that partition s always
happen. That's true. But here in the
pace LC theorem, what I want to explain
to everybody is the following. In a
multi-node system, in a multi-achine
systems, partition can anyway happen. Is
everybody with me? Partitions can always
happen. They are a given. Which means
that you must select between consistency
and availability. Is everybody with me?
You must select between consistency,
availability. You can either have a
system which is highly consistent or you
can have a system which is highly
available. That's true. We are on the
same page. The else part that I've
written here does not mean that I am
saying that partition will not even
happen.
Right?
The else part is
the else part is that
even when you forget about partitioning
right even when partition is not even
considered for now because partition
happen at times it happens when it
happens and you have to select between
aility or a or consistency.
But what this theorem wants to tell you
is that even when the system is running
normally and the partition right now has
not happened right even then consistency
and avail and latency are opposite to
each other they are fighting with each
other have I made myself clear now have
I made myself clear somewhat more clear
now that I'm not saying that I'm
building a system where partition will
not happen I am saying that of Of
course, partitions will happen. But even
at the normal running of the system,
when partitions have not happened right
now, everybody's able to communicate
with each other for now. Even then, you
have to think between even when
partition is not considered, you have to
think between consistency and low
latency. Have I made myself clear now?
Ajit are we on the same page now
that we are in a way talking about that
even without partitions consistency if
you want to have high consistency you
will have to compromise with your
latency. I hope I have made myself
clear. Why do we have that latency? I
will explain this with the same example.
To make my system highly consistent,
Hardep had to wait before telling the
user that your request is done because
Hardep had to go and write the same
thing on the other machine as well. How
many of you understand this? How many of
you understand this? That Hard had to go
and write on the same other machine as
well. This extra hop, these extra
compute time, etc. is going to take
time. Am I making sense to everybody?
Which means that if I wanted a system to
be highly consistent, I will compromise
on the on the latency.
Is everybody in the class with me? Is
everybody in the class with me? Is
everybody in the class with me? Low
latency basically means fast. Yes. Yes.
Yes. Okay. So that was the confusion.
Latency basically means the time it
takes.
Low latency
basically means fast. It is taking less
time. High latency
basically means slow. It is taking more
time. So I understand where the people
get confused. People got confused that
hey high availability was a good thing.
High consistency was a good thing and
they were imagining high latency to be a
good thing. Is that where the confusion
was stemming? High latency basically
means the system is slow. High latency
is a bad thing. Low latency is a good
thing. Guys, am I making myself clear to
everybody? If your system has low
latency, it means it is fast. So I hope
I have made myself clear. I hope all of
these things are clear. Now I will
circle back and complete the discussion
with what I discussed in the very
beginning the replication and I will
discuss a bunch of things with respect
to low latency and high consistency
again. Okay. So let me explain that. Let
me explain that uh Karunamachi with some
more topic that I have to teach. I will
tie it with your doubt. Okay? So I will
teach something new and I will tie it
with your doubt so that your doubt also
gets resolved. So what do I want from
everybody else? Focus on the next topic.
The doubt of availability sorry uh
latency and consistency would also get
clarified. Cool. So now there are some
people hoping for a break. So guys I
have promised that I will end the class
by 11:45 or 11:50. Okay. So I cannot
afford a very big break but I cannot I
don't I'm not a bad person at heart you
know I'm not somebody who is very bad at
heart so even if if you are asking for
breaks so so hopefully I will allow a 1
minute break okay so it's 11:32 right
now given that I am a very good person
at heart I allow you guys to come back
at 11:34 and then we continue is that
fine
okay
And one request is folks always revisit
the lecture right always revisit the
lecture. We discussed so many
interesting things so many important
things always revisit
and this is going to be very very
fruitful if you revisit the lectures.
Yeah.
Cool.
Okay. 11:34. We still have time.
Uh, thanks for saying that, Rishal.
Yeah, I took that liberty, Manu. I took
the liberty. I have not I I'm still
sitting on the seat, but yeah, I took
that liberty to get something done.
Uh
yeah, Anur, we'll we'll get that done
also. Okay.
Yeah, show I understand that. I
understand that. It's very easy for me
to say that revise the lecture
but difficult for you to do but still
try to understand I have to say what I
feel is the right thing to do and you
have to do what you possibly can. So
Manu know I have never been a scalar
student but I have been teaching at
scalar right from the very beginning. So
I was one of the first few people to
join Scala. I have been teaching
actually. So yeah, I joined Scala when
it was called interview bit and only the
first batch or so was had started. So I
joined from the second batch or so.
Yeah. Uh
don't worry. I am doing my we are doing
our best to make you appreciate the
concepts and the project module will
give you a lot more insight and that
will sort of make you a much better
system designer overall right
now thanks a lot for saying this cool
okay okay so I hope everybody's back
I hope everybody's back and let's get
started yeah I will share the notes as
well.
Cool. Let's get started. Uh yeah, let's
get started. So, I want everybody's
attention. Uh let's get started and
let's complete the discussion for today
with the last thing. Yeah. Yeah. S I I
understood it. I will do that. I want
everybody's attention back here. Right.
We were discussing about replication. Do
you remember replication guys? Do you
remember replication?
You remember replication? So there is
one specific kind of replication that I
want to discuss today and the other
replications will be discussed in the
storage classes later. But one
replication which I sort of discussed at
the very beginning of the lecture as
well which is that uh basically sharding
is that you dividing your data amongst
different machines. Replication is that
you taking a machine and creating copies
of it so that you can you can handle a
bit more load. Is everybody with me?
What is replication? You copy the data,
right? So one very popular way of
replication and the way that I replicate
there was is called as master slave
replication. Okay? So it's called master
slave replication.
So what is master slave replication?
Master slave replication is that you
have a master box which is the ultimate
source of truth. you call it the master
and you then you create a bunch of
slaves.
Now honestly in today's world master
slave is not the most politically
correct word to use. I forgot what
people call it these days. Uh I'm sorry.
So I will use a master slave uh word
even now. But yeah uh I hope you
appreciate the fact that yeah you can
you can call it leader follower
orchestrator worker maybe not the
correct terminology here bisujit but
yeah I hope everybody appreciates master
slave is that there is one main leader
follower yeah that's that's a more
generic thing to do say but master slave
is something which people still use and
I want you to appreciate it completely
so I will keep on using master slave so
you have a master uh this is act uh okay
active active active passive is a
different discussion My dear friend
Koshik I will discuss that later but
here just focus on this now there is a
master there is a main copy and there
are slaves which are the copies of it
right which are the replicas of it right
so the master slave replication
essentially is as follows that all your
rights
are performed on the master because your
master is the ultimate source of truth
but all all your reads
can happen from the slave slaves and
slaves can also be called as read
replicas. So you have read replicas. You
have replicas of your master at multiple
places so that your reads can happen
parallelly from different machines. How
many of you understand the concept of
master slave that you have read replicas
that you have created? Why this
relevant? How many of you appreciate
that a lot of systems that you see
around have a lot higher read load as
compared to the right load? How many of
you appreciate that? Let's look at
Facebook. There is one person who post
makes a post and there are 100 people
who read that post. There is one person
who makes a post on LinkedIn and there
are thousand people who read that post.
The reads are always in most of the
systems much much higher than the rights
and hence the read load is going to be a
lot higher which means that you require
a lot more uh a lot more uh AR a lot
more infrastructure to support your
right to support your reads. Guys, am I
making sense?
Am I making sense? Uh likes and comments
are also treated as rights my dear
friend Manu. But try to understand Manu
that even if you make one comment that
comment is going to be read by a lot
more people. So even when you think
about the right comment uh a comment as
a right the read of that comment is also
going to be a lot higher than the right
of the comment. Is that making sense
Manu? Right. The YouTubers keep on
saying please comment on my photo,
comment on my video, comment on video.
Nobody comments but whenever somebody
comments everybody's there to read that
comment right so systems most of the
systems are read heavy which means that
it makes sense to have read replicas is
everybody in the class with me it makes
sense to have read replicas so you will
distribute your read traffic across read
replicas they will read from there and
you will write on the master this is
what is called as a master slave
replication now my dear friends I will
tie this uh do you categorize Gmail as
read heavy do You categorize Gmail as
read heavy re Gmail will have
not that big a read and write
distribution. Okay Prashant but a lot
other systems will have a lot more
evident read and write uh distribution.
Okay, Gmail will of course have more
number of reads and write but the
distribution will not be as big a factor
as you see in a lot of other systems. Is
that correct Prashant? Is that correct?
I hope that makes sense. But even for
Gmail, of course, the reads are going to
be much higher than the rights. Okay.
Yeah, Srajit, you're right. Uh
yeah. So yes, Aima, your rights are
going to go to the master box. Your
reads are going to go to the read
replicas. Is everybody in the class with
me? Is this concept of master slave
clear to everybody? I already explained
replication. Now I just give it a new
name, master slave replication. Now I
want to tie it with the idea of
consistency and latency. Do I have
everybody's attention? Consistency. What
did consistency mean? Consistency mean
that every read
will
return
the latest write. Is that correct? Every
read will return the latest right. What
is latency?
Latency is the amount
of time
it takes
for the request
to be processed. Is that correct?
Latency means the amount of time it
takes for the request to be processed.
Now, everybody understands that low
latency is a good thing, guys. Are you
with me? Low latency is a good thing.
High latency is a bad thing because
latency is the amount of time it takes
for the request to be processed. Now I
want everybody to appreciate this with
respect to master slave replication.
I have a master
I have a bunch of slaves.
Let's say my friend uh V Prasad
is writing something
and when Vap Prasad writes the right
gets registered here.
Understand that there are multiple ways
that you can go about it. One way is
that whenever right happens you write it
and then you send an acknowledgement to
Vaprasad that okay your right is done
and now in an offline fashion
whatever Vap Prasad wrote gets written
to all these boxes one by one. How many
of you understand this? This is one way
to look at it that whenever Vap Prasad
writes their right is written on the
master and you send an acknowledgement.
Vap Prasad goes back home happy and now
offline system you write it on three,
you write it on four, you write it on
five.
How many of you understand that this is
going to have low latency?
Because you are not letting V Prasad
wait. V Prasad is not waiting for the
right to be done on all the boxes. But
do you think this system has very high
consistency? Do you think this system
has very high consistency? No. Because V
Prasad's right is done. But if somebody
else wants to read in the meanwhile,
they will go to a slave replica that
might not be persisted on the slave yet.
And hence they might not read a
consistent value. How many of you
understand this? How many of you
understand this? This is also low
consistency.
There is another thing that that people
call low consistency. As people can call
it low consistency or some other people
can say that okay I have ensured
eventual consistency.
What does eventual consistency mean? It
means eventually it will get consistent
but it is not consistent even right now.
Am I making sense to everybody? Does
everybody appreciate this?
Right. So it's not very high on
consistency. It's very low on latency.
So it's we are happy with respect to low
latency but we are sad with respect to
low consistency
right now let's consider another
approach how somebody else can structure
this. So somebody else can structure it
in the following manner that you have a
master. You have a bunch of slaves,
you have a master, you have slaves and
now our friend V Prasad is still
writing.
My friend Vaprasad writes something.
What does he write? Whenever he writes,
I do the following.
So you write the first thing that
happens is it gets written in the
master. Then I am waiting for all the
slaves to write it.
Only when all the slaves have written
only then I tell varasad that your job
is done. How many of you understand what
I'm saying? How many of you understand
what I'm saying? That only when all the
slaves have written only then I tell
vapasad that this is done. How many of
you understand that this is high
consistency?
How many of you understand that this is
high consistency?
You all can also call high consistency
as immediate consistency. How many of
you understand that anybody who reads
will get the data?
But this so this is a great thing. This
has high consistency but unfortunately
it has high latency as well because the
time that people will take to register
it on the slaves will keep varasad
waiting.
How many of you understand this guys?
Ajit if I remember correctly Ajit was
the one who did not understand the why
latency and consistency are inversely
prop are are competing. Ajit if you are
there in the class do you now appreciate
it my dear friend? I'm not sure if
you're there in the class or not. Do you
now appreciate it? Or I'm not even sure
if Ajit was the person who had this
doubt. Whosoever had this doubt, is this
now more clear to you guys that
consistency and latency are in a way
competing with each other.
There can be other ways in which you can
do master slave replication. Do you want
me to cover them as well?
Yes, Nicl, I will cover that as well. Do
you want me to cover some more details
about master slave? So the class can be
considered over. It's 11:45. Anybody
wants to leave, they can leave. But I
will just share some more details. Those
are additional details. If you want to
stay back, you can stay back. And then
after that, I will take all your doubts
and I will stay for as long as you want
me to stay. Now let me teach you some
more things about it. There can be other
ways as well. Yeah, the topic is over. S
I'm just going deeper into the woods. If
you want to stay back, you can stay
back. If you want to go home and sleep,
you can do that as well. Okay. Okay, I
hope that's clear. Anybody who wants to
anybody who wants to go, I would I would
thank you for attending the lecture.
Thanks a lot for attending the lecture.
It was a pleasure interacting with all
of you. I hope to see you guys again
sometime and I wish you all the very
best. Do the best in your interviews.
Make the most out of the scalar course
and get a great job. Right, Santos? Your
answer is yes. Your comment is right. It
is the it is the uh reason right. So uh
I it was a pleasure interacting with all
of you. Thanks a lot. Anybody who wants
to leave can leave. Uh wishing you all
the very best. Uh and do the best. Thank
you. Uh Saki I'm already teaching a
different batch so that might not be
possible but yeah we might see each
other again sometime later in the
future. Okay guys so I will go deeper
into the woods. If you want to stay back
you can stay back right. So other ways
in which you can do master slave
replication is the following. You have a
master,
you have a bunch of slaves,
right?
When V Prasad comes and writes
something,
right? I will write it on master
and I will ensure that at least some of
the slaves have the right with them. So
I will not wait for all the slaves to
give me the right. I will call the right
on all of them. But the moment let's say
somebody or some x number of slaves give
me a right that hey they have registered
the right then I will tell var prasad to
that your job is done guys am I making
sense am I making sense that I will not
wait for all the slaves to register the
right I will wait for some x number of
slaves to register the right is that
making sense that's another way you are
in a way choosing somewhere in between
high consistency and low latency you are
choosing somewhere in between right uh
this is called by different names prasad
and we will discuss this later in the
following classes with more detail but I
just wanted to pinpoint this and I
wanted to pinpoint one more interesting
fact about it when we discussed the
first approach where you only write on
the master and tell verasad your job is
done there is a problem with it your
durability might get compromised what
does that mean it means that What if
what if something physically bad
happened to the master? I wrote on the
master but I did not copy it
synchronously to any of the slaves and
tomorrow
uh somebody put the master on fire
before the synchronization can happen.
Do you think that data will get lost
forever? What Vap Prasad wrote will get
lost forever. Does that make all of us
emotional? Vapra Prasad's important data
being lost forever makes me emotional at
least. Right? That that's unfortunate
thing that happened with Wrasad,
right? So you made a Facebook post and
the master got on fire. Your Facebook
post is lost forever.
That's not a good thing. So if you want
to ensure some level of durability
just writing on the master and not
copying on any of the slaves is not a
good thing to do. Am I making sense? Is
this making sense to everybody?
So in a lot of applications you would if
if your data persistence is critical if
you would not want to lose something
forever you would want to ensure that
you are consist persisting on some of
the slaves at least. Now I will give you
some examples. Is everybody ready to
take some examples? Is everybody
interested to hear some examples? Let's
hear the following examples. Let's say V
Prasad wants to write. Okay,
let's take an example that WA Prasad
wants to write a post on Facebook,
right? So they wrote a post on Facebook.
How many of you have seen this happening
that Vapras Prasad wrote a post and now
they wrote a post on their laptop but
they go and check their mobile and they
are not seeing the post. Have you seen
that happening folks? You made an
Instagram post from one particular
device. You go and see another device
but you're not seeing that post for some
time. Have you seen that? Why is that
happening? Because they are doing some
sort of eventual consistency where they
would have written on some slaves but
they have not written on every slave.
And if you go and read some other slave
you will not see that post. Does that
make you happy guys? Does that make you
happy? Isn't that amazing that we are
able to relate the real life scenario
with what we are studying in the class?
So happy from a point of view of
understanding system design. Right? On
the other hand, would it be fine if V
Prasad wrote a LinkedIn post and it was
not only not available for some time but
it is lost forever. You think that's a
good experience? It's lost forever.
That's not a good experience. We are
fine with this being eventually
consistent. We are fine with waiting for
5 minutes or 2 minutes to see the post.
But we are not fine with that post being
lost forever. Which means that for
posts, LinkedIn should not just copy on
the on the master. It must copy on some
of the slaves so that the post is not
getting lost forever. On the other hand,
I will give you another example. How
many of you have seen that you go and
like somebody's photo on Facebook
and that like got lost forever.
How many of you seen that happening? You
like a photo with your mobile phone.
You see on some other device that that
like is not there. So okay let me
explain that further. It might not
happen that once you have seen the like
it will always stay. That's true. But
have you seen that you like something
right now and
you refresh it it's not there and it
never got registered. This if you are an
avid social media user you might have
seen that. Hmon says that he has seen
that on Instagram that you like
something you refresh and you're not
seeing it and you will never see it.
Why? because that like might have gotten
lost forever. Which means that for a
like maybe it's not that critical for
you to copy on a bunch of slaves. You
can just write on the marks and you can
tell the user that it's done because
even if it's get if even if it get lost
it's not a very big deal. Guys am I
making sense? I'm trying to tell you
where to use this approach where to use
this approach where to use this
approach. Is this making sense to
everybody in the class?
Right now I will give you some examples
and you will tell me what to what to
prefer, what to use, how to build it.
Right? So let's take an example of a
banking system
from a cap theorem perspective. Would
you want your banking system to be
consistent or available? Would you want
your banking system to be consistent or
available? Consistent.
From a paceel perspective with respect
to latency and consistent, would you
want your banking system to be uh to be
very low latency that it should be very
fast or would you rather want it to be
highly consistent that even if you take
time please be consistent. So I hope
everybody in the class appreciates that
the banking systems need not be super uh
super immediate right they need not be
very low latency they may take time but
they should be consistent. Have you
noticed Google pay for example taking
some time sometimes to register your
request? You have seen that. Have you
seen any to take some time? You have
seen that it can be slightly high
latency but it should not be un
inconsistent. I hope everybody in the
class is with me. Right now let's
consider some more examples. Let's
consider the example of you looking at
Yeah. Yeah. That's a very interesting
question. I will come to that. Let's
let's look at an example of you loading
your Facebook news feed.
If a Facebook news feed is, do would you
prefer availability or would you prefer
consistency?
Consistency basically means that
whatever my friends have posted, I must
see.
Availability means that at least show me
my newsfeed. Would you be fine by
Facebook saying that hey I'm not
available let me come back but I will
ensure that all the posts are visible to
you. No, show me something man at least
show me something. So availability is
more preferable than consistency in a
Facebook newsfeed. Is everybody in the
class with me? Is everybody in the class
with me?
Second, is
low latency more important or high
consistency more important for Facebook
newsfeed? Is low latency more important
or high consistency more important? Low
latency is more important. Right? Let's
consider one more example. Let's say
Facebook Messenger. you are talking to
somebody on Facebook or let's say Google
chat or or let's say uh Slack
do you want your Slack messages to be
consistent or do you want them to be
available by consistent I mean if I send
something to S must see it if I am
seeing a red tick a blue tick s must
have gotten it right
it's it's it's not a very uh it's not a
very black and white answer different
machines that you build, different
systems that you build, different
chatting systems that you build might
have different business use cases and
you might want to choose something
different. But let me give you an give
you a scenario. You wrote I love you to
somebody and you thought that that
somebody has read the message but that
somebody never got that message. Would
you be fine with that? Would you be fine
with your chatting system to not being
consistent? No. you would you would get
in a very bad state assuming that they
ignored your message but they never got
your message. So you might imagine a
business use case where where you would
want your chatting system to be
consistent right it's a very animated
example Anurat and hence would have also
given it but on the other hand there
might be some other chatting
applications let's say you are building
a chat application for a game okay how
many of you have played massively multi
uh multiplayer games like for example
Fortnite or counterike etc where you say
something where you chat etc do you
understand that Here availability is lot
more important than consistency that if
your game has paused it has very high
latency. It is not available that is bad
as compared to consistency. There might
be a active action that you might have
done which is lost but that's fine but
it should be very low ping. It should be
very low latency at the same same time
it should be available. Guys am I making
some sense? And even a chatting
application for a gaming application
might prefer availability over
consistency. Is that making is that
making sense? Because you're not going
to go and write I love you on a chat on
a on a chat in a in a game, right? I
hope that makes sense,
right? Is WhatsApp CP or AP? So WhatsApp
is basically consistent
and it may not be available all the
time.
Have you seen that Satendra? It may not
be available all the time. Right? What
is low ping? Low ping basically means
low latency. Low ping basically means
it's replying back to your requests
quickly. Right? Cool guys. So I have
covered a bunch of things in a lot of
detail. If there are any questions I can
stay back and answer them. I see 13
questions. and I will stay and answer
them. If you want to raise your hand,
raise your hand. Would love to interact
with you and you can ask me anything
under the sun. Right. Uh
okay, I will answer unmute people one by
one. Uh Sav on WhatsApp I was saying
that hey WhatsApp needs to be consistent
more than available. Does that make
sense? S hey Vabasad please tell me
>> like uh so like uh a question was asked
in some HLD interview like for me. So I
had a system like database it is daily
refreshed at one time.
>> Okay.
>> I had some endpoints
like some web pace kind of things. So
like uh if the data is refreshing in
that scenarios like the data should be
like it should be available or it should
be consistent.
>> When you say the data is being refreshed
daily what exactly is meant by that? The
database is refreshed every day at
particular time.
>> So it it gets new new data, right? It
gets
>> Yeah, it gets new new data
>> at a particular time point in time.
>> Now what you're saying is whether you
would want your system to be available
>> or consistent.
>> Okay.
>> So like I have some VBA which some users
will be using.
>> Mhm. So in this case like whether I
should go with consistent or with uh
like
>> so that totally depends on the business
use case where Prasad. So let's talk
about what kind of a data is that you
should ask with your with your whosoever
is taking your interview and hey tell me
what kind of a use case this is what
kind of a data is this. So let me give
you both the scenarios and based on the
data you can also take a call which
makes more sense right. So try to
understand when your databases are
getting refreshed or updated your
database might get unavailable for some
time if you want it to remain highly
consistent. If you want people to get
the correct view all the time you will
have to at that point in time not
interact with the database because it's
getting updated. So you can you can say
that hey I'm choosing consistency I'm
not available for the time my databases
get updated. I'm fine with that. On the
other hand, if that's not very critical
data and you might have cached that data
somewhere or a copy of that data
somewhere. So now when the database is
getting updated, you might want to refer
that copy and and show some stale data
to the users and in a way you are
available all the time but you are not
consistent.
>> Okay. Okay. If it was a SQL DB, most
likely they would be storing data that
requires high consistency and you would
want to say that hey, I would prefer
consistency over availability. But it
depends on the use case whether you want
your system to be highly consistent at
that time and hence not being available
because it's getting updated or you are
fine with getting giving wrong data but
you're not fine with not being available
and hence you can choose availability or
consistency depends on the use case but
I have explained both the scenarios to
you. Does that make sense?
>> Yeah. Okay. Okay. Thanks. Thanks.
>> Thanks. Thanks. Thank you. Uh Ashit has
asked to be noted. Thank please tell me
and everybody who is uh telling me that
it was a good lecture. Thanks a lot for
saying that. It really means a lot. Uh
it was very nice talking to all of you.
Uh thanks a lot. Uh please Ash go on.
>> Yeah. Hi Taran. Uh yeah it's not related
to the uh consistency or availability.
It's just related to the master slave
architecture. Uh so I just want to know
how does this this architecture come
into picture when when we have a cache
or any sort of in place.
>> Okay. So master slave what I'm talking
about is respect to one system right
now. So you can discuss master slave
with respect to a with respect to a
database. You can discuss master slave
with respect to anything else but
primarily it's about database. When you
think about caching, it's a different
layer where you save a copy of what's in
the database and use that copy to serve
request. That cache might be in sync,
out of sync. So would have taught you
about uh write through, write back,
write around, etc. That's a different
scenario. But when I but when I say
master slave, I essentially mean that
hey your database boxes will have a
master will have a bunch of slaves. If
you want the master slave replication
because that will aid your that will aid
your uh reads that will also make your
data more durable. It's a different
concept. It's an orthogonal concept to
caching. It's not sort of merged with
caching. Does that make sense?
>> Okay. Okay. So it it comes into picture
only when uh we reach the database part
not
>> right. So it's it's a database layer
layer concept. Right.
>> Yeah. So is this concept applicable for
the cache layer also like if there is
>> you you can you can but the kind of the
kind of problem that a cache is solving
having master slave there does not make
a lot of sense. So master slave is a is
a very fundamental concept you can use
it anywhere but using it on caching will
not mean make a lot of sense in a lot of
cases right but in databases it will
make sense in almost every case.
>> Okay yeah thank you.
>> Thanks a lot. Thank you. Anybody else
wants to be unmuted? Nobody else wants
to be muted. So I will take the
questions on the chat and I answer them
and on the questions tab Shu has a
question but sometimes you observe that
in WhatsApp if somebody's online you
deliver the message but a single tick
takes some minutes to take double tick.
See both the person are chatting at the
same time. What's such case right? So
when it only shows you a single tick and
not a double tick understand sham that
it is throwing high latency and it is
also being in a way unavailable. So you
have sent something but that something
has not been registered. Does that make
sense to him? Have you seen on WhatsApp
that sometime WhatsApp says please re
please try resending. You might not have
seen that on WhatsApp but you have would
have seen that on Facebook chat. How
many of you have seen that on Facebook
chat that Facebook tells you your
message could not be delivered please
try resending. Have you seen that? You
might have seen that on WhatsApp as
well. That is your system being
unavailable at that time and choosing
consistency. On the other hand, you
might have also seen that somebody you
sent a message but you are only getting
a single tick, not getting a double
tick, which means that your latency for
delivery is high but WhatsApp is trying
WhatsApp is trying to be consistent for
you. Am I making sense for everybody?
Does that make sense?
That's great.
Yes, Shbam.
Uh most likely I will be in unc
inconsistent for your batch. Karu Mangi.
Uh
yes. So yeah distributed caches like
radius you can have master slave
architecture there and I will maybe uh
maybe reddis will be discussed in great
detail. If it is not discussed I will
share some resources on redisk and you
can go through them. I have taken a
bunch of classes on redisk. I can share
them with you.
So for that you can reach out to the
scaler support and they can help you
with that.
Uh so most of the SQL systems do not
natively support it but a lot of systems
SQL system have started to support it
even if the SQL system does not support
it out of the box. You can configure it
yourself. You will require some sort of
a zookeeper or some sort of a manager at
the top. So you'll have to have some
abstraction layer and you can you can do
that.
Cool. I will now take questions from the
uh from the Okay. What are the
strategies for high revy systems? High
heavy systems are basically master
master systems. Prague will teach you
that in one of the storage classes. So
master master will be covered later.
So let me let me go through the
questions. Let me go through the
questions and answer them one by one. Uh
I will go to the question which is asked
which is uploaded the most or maybe I
can go to the most recent question. So
the recent question is how replication
happen in the slaves if new rights are
performed on the master. Can we discuss
more scenarios and slave can go down and
master can go down. So replication there
can be multiple ways in which
replication can run sunk. It can be
either in a synchronized fashion that
while a right is done you ensure that it
is written on the slave and only then
you tell the master then then you tell
the user that right is done. This is
called as sync. Uh this is one way.
Another way can be that you do in an
offline fashion as I discussed that you
can write later. Now what can happen if
this master goes down and there is some
slave which has the latest right then a
new master will get elected. There is
called as something called master
election protocol and a new master will
get elected out of the present slaves
and it will start acting as a master.
There are a lot of other concepts to be
discussed here which we'll discuss in
the next few classes. Okay Sankit I hope
I have answered this now. Can you throw
some light on cap theorem versus asset
in cases of databases? So asset is a
asset is a property of SQL databases uh
where you have atomicity consistency uh
and uh durability and uh I am just
missing the term of I but I I I can
explain that. So basically it's
isolation levels. So that's something
which is totally something different to
do with SQL databases. Cap theorem is
not sort of directly related to it. So I
I can't draw a parallel between them.
Why network is called unreliable? For
example, let's say there is a sub 10
machines in the subset. How can the
network be unreliable? Koshik, network
is always unreliable. Network is always
something which you cannot bank on all
the time. It's not something that uh
it's not something that uh will function
all the time. It can always be
unavailable. Uh this is the
characteristic of the network. The
network basically means that there are a
lot of moving parts involved for your
message from the source to be delivered
to the destination. There are so many
moving parts involved and anything can
be down and hence your message need not
get transferred whenever you want them
to be transferred. So it's always
unreliable. S which protocol is used for
combination with replicas? Please
discuss master slave versus peer-to-peer
and other application strategy.
Peer-to-peer is different. It's somewhat
of a master master. Master slave is one
place to write multiple places to read
from. Uh what protocols are used?
Different protocols are used for
different scenarios. There are some
popular master save application
protocols. You can read more about them
uh yourself. Uh then there's a question
how will we deal with HTTP request?
Consider case request received first
services down when we are making copy
till that no response. Uh yeah so the
request will get dropped. Rohit you will
have to reinitiate a request and that
reinitiated request will get answered.
Koshik asked the question during
replication is the source node brought
down right keeps on happening. I have
already answered that Koshik that there
can be multiple ways you can either do
it in sync or you can do it out of sync.
If you have more questions you can raise
your hand. Uh Rohit has unmuted has
asked to be muted. Rohit I will unmute
you. Please tell me what your question
is.
So the concern is we have a contact with
like a client and server.
>> Mhm.
>> So whenever we do the HTTP call so we
are we have contact within 5 seconds we
will respond you. Okay.
>> But this is the fault from our side
right we are getting the data and we are
copying into our replica. Okay.
>> So initially it was very happily going.
Okay. we are copy in our sharding and uh
immediate we are responsing yeah the
your task was done. Now if in any case
like uh if during the sharding my uh
database will uh down then I will look
another place where multiple replica
master slave or some something which can
be we have make if this one down we will
uh copy in another but during this time
the time stamp whatever we have tell we
will respond 5 second it took 7 second
now what we will response to that uh
client API like the data log cost or we
will say like uh internal server error
like uh this was the concern.
>> Yes, you can basically throw a timeout
request, right? If you have a 5-second
uh time uh under which you want your
APIs to be responded to, you can send a
timeout request or you can send a late
response. It's up to the client how they
are going to either they are going to
wait or they're going to drop and resend
the request. That's totally on the
client. On the other hand, if your
server internally is down, you can send
a uh you can send a internal server
error uh error code and tell the client
that hey maybe you should retry. I'm not
able to process it right now.
>> So uh so if consider this send a request
we have copied in our database and while
uh uh copying over the replica it's
somehow we exceed the time. So we will
tell through timeout exception and then
again that data whatever they send that
I will lose then again they need to send
that request.
>> Oh got it. Oh now I understood your
question. No no no that's not how it
will happen. So understand it. So Rohit
let's say somebody uh sent to you a
request to write something right.
>> Yes.
>> Now you will write it to your master.
You will if if your if your if your
algorithm is that you would want to copy
to your slaves and then return back to
the client saying that hey it is now
written you will then do it and then
return back. On the other hand if you
have a scenario where you have a some
sort of a very strict SLA that my
request should only be written in 5
seconds unless and until unless that
happens I will send a timeout uh reply.
If that is what is happening then if by
chance you could not adhere to that
timeline then you will have to undo the
right in whatever copies you have
written so that the database overall is
in consistent shape. Does that make
sense right?
>> Yes.
>> On the other hand you would rather not
want to build a system like that where
this happens frequently because you
would want to keep your timeout uh or
your fan factor in such a manner that
this does not happen usually. But in the
cases this happens, you will have to
roll back your updates and tell the user
it's a timeout and they will have to
resend so that everybody's on the same
page with respect to the consistent
state of the database. Does that make
sense?
>> Yes, that is actually making the sense
>> right.
>> So like instead of if time out I'm
sending then I should roll back
everything. So whenever
>> of course you should you should ensure
that everything is consistent.
Absolutely.
>> Absolutely. Yeah. Fine.
>> Okay. Thank you. Thank you. And one more
thing Tarun so in this uh in this uh
what to say in the cap theorem so if we
say the availability and partition
tolerance if we take at a time then
eventually we can take the consistency
also correct
>> you're right you're absolutely right you
can always have a scenario where you
choose availability and partition
tolerance and with respect to
consistency you are being eventually
consistent you are not losing out on the
rights you're eventually being
consistent absolutely Yeah like within
we can schedule one scheduleul a job
which will work on within 1 hour or two
hour it will take data here and there.
So the during the time between after the
1 hour we waited each other that time we
are not consistent but after that
immediate it will be consistent. So for
the high throughput when we have a very
high data and where we want a little bit
consistency in that case we can use that
right. If we want very high consistency
then we need to deal with either
partition tolerance or availability.
>> You're absolutely right. So that's
that's a wonderful uh point and I can in
fact uh write it down here as well
because this is worth noting in the cap
theorem the C that I talked about was in
a way immediate consistency
because you can of course have eventual
consistency even while being available
right yes
>> when I say if you are building a
available and partition tolerant system
it does not mean that you are going to
lose out on your data if somebody was
something was written it is not
immediate consistent which means that
some other people can read some older
version of the data for now but it's not
the case that the new right will be lost
forever it is going to be persisted
eventually so when I say the tradeoff
the trade-off is between immediate
consistency and availability
>> and
yeah
>> and this in this uh uh B A C LC in this
elgo this algorithm we are using like uh
because the cap theorem is very famous
right so
>> yeah cap theorem is very famous paste LC
is more of a extension to it it's not
contradicting cap theorem cap theorem is
what it is it is just extending it and
just making you appreciate the fact that
even without the partition happening the
latency and consistency are somewhat in
a competition with each If you want to
build a very high consistent system, you
might have to indulge in higher latency
also and vice versa. So it's it's sort
of a extension. It talks about some
another parameter beyond the capture. So
it's not a not a anti-capore thing or
not a not a opposite to capum. It's just
something more than what the capum says.
Are we on the same page now?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So only the thing tu so like
uh since you worked on good organization
so many places so really we are using in
any our any very famous application like
Facebook Twitter like there are so many
applications so somehow some places is
we really using this PSC algorithm it's
it's not about us using it or not using
it right it basically is a theorem it
tells you that any system that you build
you will face such a scenario it's not
as if I'm using tap theorem and
necessarily creating a scenario where I
have to choose it in cons consistency
availability. It's a theorem which says
that at a very fundamental level
whatever you build you'll have to choose
it in consistency and availability.
Similarly, pace healthcy theorem is a
fundamental theorem which tells you that
if you want high consistency please be
ready to understand that it will mean
high latency also. So it's more of a
knowledge that you have. It's not as if
you have to use it or choose to not use
it. It's a it's a comment on the systems
that you build that whenever you want to
build a highly consistent system,
latency will automatically creep in.
Does that make sense?
>> It's not something that you use or
choose to not use. It's something which
is summarizing some information about
systems that you should know so you can
design better systems. Does that make
sense?
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> Okay. Thanks a lot.
>> One more question I have.
>> Yeah, there are other also waiting
right. I also have to go.
>> Yeah, just small. So you told like intra
and intro there will when we do the
sharding. So uh like will you let me
know right now or some other classes. So
>> right. So intra and inter sharding these
are the concept which will be discussed
later in the I will just give you a
brief answer to it. Intra intrashard
request basically means the request that
can be answered through a sing a query
on a single machine a single shot.
Intershard request basically means that
a query that needs to be answered
through for which multiple machines will
have to run something they will have to
collaborate and give you an answer. So
intershard queries with respect to
databases are always very tough very
very time consuming it overflows the
system overruns the system intrashard
queries is what you usually prefer. So
do you want to ask something else? It
should be covered later. But yeah, if
you want to ask something.
>> So whatever the intra you are telling
like in that we need to dig multiple
system that means in the particular
>> intra basically means single system.
Inter basically means multiple system.
>> Inter. So whatever the inter you mean to
save. So there will be some like uh
databases are there there multiple
sharding are there. So in that the first
first task find out my relative sharding
and then in inside that then we need to
dig and intra means like specific to me.
I know blindly I'm going over there and
I'm searching in enter multiples are
there first I need to find out my type
of
>> not necessarily first you have a query
which requires multiple shards to
process it
>> because the data might be spread in
multiple shards this is what is called
as enter if you have a query for which
the data is present inside a single
shard it is called as intra
>> yeah got it that example we have taken a
friend and right so there can be
multiple examples that you can build.
This might not be the right time because
it will take me 10 minutes to construct
an example. But the simple idea is that
inter basically means a query which
needs to be run across multiple machines
to get your job done. Intra basically
means that you can go to a single shard
and just do it there you are done right.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Correct. Correct. That a
friend and a person example will work.
If friend person is single it will be
the inter and if friend is other then it
will be the inter. Yeah.
>> Yes. You're right. You're right.
>> Thanks. Thanks. Thanks.
>> Thanks a lot, Rohit. Thanks a lot. Have
a great night. Thanks a lot for asking
good questions. Thank you. Now, uh,
whosoever wants to be invited? Uh,
Sankit asked, uh, why do we choose
between X slaves to write in a standard
three? How is it helpful? Sankit, it's
helpful because you are ensuring that
your data never gets lost. one. Second,
you are ensuring that uh that at least
some parts of the system are going to
read the latest right and in in a way
you have started that eventual
consistency process up front but
primarily it's with respect to
durability so that your data is never
lost forever. Okay. Shankit also asked
what is more important for trading
platforms in terms of cap. In terms of
cap theorem, trading platforms will
always want to prefer consistency. You
should not be in a scenario where you
bought some shares at 1042 rupees
according to you but later you realize
that you bought them at 1080. Does that
make sense? It should not be the case
that you are told a misinformation right
now and later you are told that okay
this is not the price at which you
bought you bought at some other price.
So consistency is more important.
Trading platforms at times can be
unavailable and that's also a very big
deal. Trading platforms are one of the
toughest system design to build. Uh but
how many of you remember some time ago
there was a time when zerodha was
unavailable. It was some expiry day uh
where these contracts were getting
expired and a lot of people wanted to
place a lot of orders. The market was
fluctuating a lot and people were not
able to place orders and hence they lost
a lot of money because zerodha was not
available. So it can it can happen but
they will still have to prefer
consistency over availability because if
they want to be available and they don't
worry about consistency then they will
have to pay money from their pockets
right if they let you buy at wrong
prices then who's going to who's going
to pay that money right so uh so it must
be consistent it can at times be
unavailable it's going to be a big news
it's going to be a big thing but at
times it can be unavailable consistency
is more important right and similarly
latency even though They need to be very
low latency systems. But still
consistency is more important than
ensuring low latency. They cannot
compromise with consistency.
Yeah, you are right. There are some
crypto exchanges which used to be
inconsistent but but yeah crypto is
better left unset. Uh the kind of
ecosystem that there was it's better
left unsaid. Uh Anurak says how is
consistency maintained in replicas? I
think I've already answered it.
Partitioning versus sharding. Sharding
is due dividing data in different uh
machines. Partitioning is also the same
concept but people get confused because
partitioning is also used in cap theorem
but that is network partitioning. When
you say partitioning of data that is
essentially sharding anur I hope I've
answered that. Uh
now can you explain user and friends
data? How are they in the same chart? H
let's that's some a question of a
different class ideally that should be
covered in the last class when you did
caching uh I don't have time I guess to
explain that to you right now so I will
pause that question for a while anurak
says there will be multiple tables
present where user ID might be the
primary key so what particular user ID
all the data yeah Anra so that's a call
that you have to take on a casebyase
basis you will not be able to do that
for every table you will have to take a
call or for what tables you have to do
it. Okay, there are still so many
questions. Ajit says suppose from client
side I want to access user two user in
one request user one in shard a how
retrieval happens this will become a
intershard request my dear friend Aji
and it's not that great great a thing uh
a club asks does myql or any db natively
support sharding by default uh a club
I've already answered that there are a
bunch of SQL DBs which today support
this out of the box but even if it does
not to put it out of the box. You can
still configure it by having some sort
of a manager on top of it, some sort of
abstraction layer on top of it. Uh but
there are lots and lots of NoSQL DBs
which does it out of the box for you.
Vishujit asks if there is a table that
does not have direct user ID, how does
the data in that that's more of a that's
more of a uh low-level design question.
So not the right platform to ask it. I
would have answered it but understand
it's already 12:30 I also have to go and
sleep. uh hence I did not answer it
right now. It's because it's not a
question for today's class but yeah
maybe sometime else when we have time I
can answer that as well. So in case of
DB down migration of each data will
happen right. So for each row we will
calculate shard number and send it over
there. Yeah this is slow this happens
but this is usually prevented by you
having master slave architecture uh and
you not having to move data because you
already have that data copied in a
slave.
Oh, how was Google interview what was
asked? Not a relevant question for
today's class, my dear friend. We can
discuss that sometime later.
Uh
yeah, cost has a very very big role in
deciding what system to build. uh
whatever you do uh whatever we do uh is
has an implication of cost and that's a
very very important factor in system
design otherwise you can say that hey I
will I will buy all the systems in this
world I will build a cache of 1,000 TB
everything will be served from cash you
can claim that but that's not
practically possible because you will
have to shove a lot of money so system
design decisions need to take into
account the money that you can possibly
spend. Okay, cool. I I use a phrase uh
which you can always use. I always say
cashing swadus or for people who do not
understand Hindi cashing as per your
taste. I am taking reference from the
idea of a master chef episode where
people will say that hey you add namak
you add salt as per your taste.
Similarly you can say caching swadasar
you add cashing wherever you want to do
based on the amount of money that you
can spend and the kind of use case that
you have. So yeah uh that sort of uh
tries and borrows the idea that hey
money is very important in taking
decisions and decisions. Uh Hush wanted
to ask about uh I am tempted to answer
it for you Hush but I'm very late also.
Hush are you there in the class? Are you
there in the class? You're in there in
the class. Okay. So this is the last
question that I will answer. I may not
be able to answer it completely but I
will partially answer it with whatever
time I have. Uh Nikl just uh remind me
in a day or two I will find those
lectures and ask support to share with
you. Okay cool. So let me look at hers's
question. Uh can you explain user and
friends data? How are they in the same
chart?
Should I also have my friend's data in
the same chart?
Okay. So, h that's not possible, right?
So, you let's say are a user 107. You
sit in a particular share where are your
friends 668, 1070, 1114 and so on and so
forth. You can never come up with a
system where all your friends will
definitely be in the same chart. Are you
with me Hersh? You can never have a
scenario like that because you can
potentially become friends with anybody
tomorrow. Let's say if I have
partitioning like this, even let's say
all your friends are in the same shard.
But now if you make a friendship with
668,
how will I put all of you in the same
shard? You would always have scenarios
where your friends are in different
shards. But what I wanted to convey is
that the user friends table where the
mapping of all the friend ids of yours
that should be present in your chart so
that at least you can know who all your
friends are. But if you want to go
inside the posts of your friends, you'll
have to go to a different shard. Have I
made myself clear my dear friend? Uh
hush. I never claimed that all your
friends are going to be in the same
shard. I just claim that at least your
mapping which all friend ids you have
should be in the same shard. And given
all your friends cannot be in the same
shard. Hence the solution that Prague
would have given for the news Facebook
news feed where he made a new copy of
recent posts. That was the solution
because of that reason itself because
you cannot ensure all your friends to be
in the same shot. Does that make sense?
Hush.
Thank you. Thank you everyone. It was a
pleasure interacting with all of you. I
wish you all the best. See you again.
Uh bye-bye.
Thanks a lot everyone. Thanks a lot.